<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: literal | Nick Desaulniers]]></title>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/categories/literal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-01T23:11:26-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Desaulniers]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Designated initialization with compound literals in C]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/designated-initialization-with-pointers-in-c/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T16:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/designated-initialization-with-pointers-in-c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick post on something I just discovered and found neat (I always find
obscure C syntax interesting).  I was trying to figure out how to use a C
designated initializer, where a member was a pointer to another designated
initializer.  At this point, you need a compound literal.  Just a quick
background on C initialization:</p>

<p>```c
// verbosely create an array with a known size
int arr [3];
arr[0] = 1;
arr[1] = 2;
arr[2] = 3;
// => [1, 2, 3]</p>

<p>// concisely create an array with a known size
int arr [3] = { 1, 2, 3 }; // => [1, 2, 3]</p>

<p>// creates an array with unspecified values initialized to 0
int arr [4] = { 1, 2, 3 }; // => [1, 2, 3, 0]</p>

<p>// truncates declaration
int arr [1] = { 1, 2, 3 }; // => [1]</p>

<p>// based on number of initializers
int arr [] = { 1, 2, 3 }; // => [1, 2, 3]
```</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at how we might have initialized a struct in C89.  In C89, you are
required to declare local variables at the top of a block.  A previous
initialization of a point struct might have looked like:</p>

<p>```c
struct point {
  int x, y;
};</p>

<p>{
  struct point a;
  a.x = 2;
  a.y = 3;
}
```</p>

<p>Just as we can define array literals in C using the initializer list syntax, we
can use the same concise syntax for initializing structs!</p>

<p><code>c
// point a is located at (2, 3)
struct point a = { 2, 3 };
</code></p>

<p>Well, this can be bad.  Where would point a be located if say a fellow team
mate came along and modified the definition of the point struct to:</p>

<p><code>c
struct point {
  int y, x; // used to be `int x, y;`
};
</code></p>

<p>Suddenly point a points to (3, 2), not (2, 3).  It&rsquo;s better if you use
designated initializers to declare the values for members of your struct.  It&rsquo;s
up to the compiler to decide on the order of initialization, but it wont mess
up where the data is intended to go.</p>

<p><code>c
// point b is located at (2, 3)
struct point b = { .y = 3, .x = 2 };
</code></p>

<p>So now we have designated initializers, cool.  What about if we want to use the
same syntax to reassign point b?</p>

<p><code>c
b = { .x = 5, .y = 6 };
//    ^
// error: expected expression
</code></p>

<p>While you are being explicit about the shape of the struct that you are trying
to assign to b, the compiler cannot figure out that you&rsquo;re trying to assign a
point struct to another point struct.  A C cast would probably help here and
that&rsquo;s what the concept of compound literals are.</p>

<p><code>c
b = (struct point) { .x = 5, .y = 6 }; // works!
</code></p>

<p>Notice: I just combined a compound literal with a designated initializer.  A
compound literal on its own would look like:</p>

<p><code>c
b = (struct point) { 5, 6 }; // works!
</code></p>

<p>To recap we can define points like so:</p>

<p><code>c
struct point a;
a.x = 1;
a.y = 2; // C89 (too verbose)
struct point b = { 3, 4 }; // initializer list (struct member order specific)
struct point c = { .x = 5, .y = 6 }; // designated initializer (non struct member order specific)
struct point d = (struct point) { .x = 7, .y = 8 }; // compound literal (cast + designated initialization)
</code></p>

<p>My favorite part of compound literals is that you can define values inline of
an argument list.  Say you have a function prototype like:</p>

<p>```c
int distance (struct point, struct point);</p>

<p>// instead of calling it like this
// (creating temp objects just to pass in)
struct point a = { .x = 1, .y = 2 };
struct point b = { .x = 5, .y = 6 };
distance(a, b);</p>

<p>// we can use compound literals
distance((struct point) { .x = 1, .y = 2 }, (struct point) { .x = 5, .y = 6 });
```</p>

<p>So compound literals help with reassignment of structs, and not storing
temporary variables just to pass as function arguments.  What happens though
when one of your members is a pointer?  C strings are easy because they already
have a literal value:</p>

<p>```c
struct node {
  char <em>value;
  struct node </em>next;
};</p>

<p>// just using designated initialization
struct node a = {
  .value = “hello world”,
  .next = NULL
};
```</p>

<p>But what happens if we want to initialize node.next?  We could do:</p>

<p><code>c
struct node b = {
  .value = “foo”,
  .next = NULL
};
a.next = &amp;b;
</code></p>

<p>Again, we have to define b before assigning it to a.next.  That&rsquo;s worthwhile if
you need to reference b later in that scope, but sometimes you don&rsquo;t (just like
how compound literals can help with function arguments)!  But that&rsquo;s where I
was stumped.  How do you nest designated initializers when the a member is a
pointer to another designated initializer?  A first naïve attempt was:</p>

<p>```c
struct node c = {
  .value = “bar”,
  .next = {</p>

<pre><code>.value = “baz”,
</code></pre>

<p>//  ^
// error: designator in initializer for scalar type &lsquo;struct node *&rsquo;</p>

<pre><code>.next = NULL
</code></pre>

<p>  }
};
```</p>

<p>WTF?  Well, if you go back to the example with nodes a and b, we don&rsquo;t assign
the value of b to a.next, we assign it a pointer to b.  So how can we use
designated initializers to define, say, the first two nodes of a linked list?
Compound literals.  Remember, a compound literal is essentially a designated
initialization + cast.</p>

<p>```c
struct node d = {
  .value = “qux”,
  .next = &amp;((struct node) {</p>

<pre><code>.value = “fred”,
.next = NULL
</code></pre>

<p>  })
};
```</p>

<p>And that works, but why?  d.next is assigned an address of a
compound literal.  Granted, you probably don&rsquo;t want to be declaring your entire
linked list like this, as nesting gets out of control fast.  I really like this
style because it reminds me of JavaScript&rsquo;s syntax for declaring object
literals.  It would look nicer if all of your nested structs were values and
not references though; then you could just use designated initializers and
wouldn&rsquo;t need compound literals or address of operators.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s your favorite or most interesting part of C syntax?</p>

<p>Acknowledgements:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://louisstowasser.com/">Louis Stowasser</a></li>
<li><a href="http://fredericiana.com/">Frederic Wenzel</a></li>
<li><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920025108.do">21st Century C</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
