<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Believe | Nick Desaulniers]]></title>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/categories/believe/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-16T23:49:51-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Desaulniers]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Internet] Freedom is Not Free]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/01/19/internet-freedom-is-not-free/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-19T20:12:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/01/19/internet-freedom-is-not-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, the Internet community
<a href="http://tech.mit.edu/V132/N61/swartz.html">lost</a> a member in the on going war
against the copyright industry.  While I&rsquo;ve never met the deceased, or
even heard of the deceased before his suicide, I&rsquo;m horrified.  I&rsquo;m
horrified that the government we are asked to put so much faith in,
would give someone, not that different from myself, such a <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120917/17393320412/us-government-ups-felony-count-jstoraaron-swartz-case-four-to-thirteen.shtml">ridiculous sentence</a>.
That I could be thrown away, locked away from the things that
I love for 35 years, for freeing information that
<a href="http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2013/01/aaron-swartz-memorial-jstor-liberator-sets-public-domain-academic-articles-free/">should</a>
have been free, and was later
<a href="http://www.3news.co.nz/Reddit-co-founder-dies-weeks-before-trial/tabid/412/articleID/282905/Default.aspx">made</a> free.</p>

<p>That my government would strike such fear into someone&rsquo;s life that they
would prefer death by their own hands to punishment.  Why do we put up
with this?</p>

<p>The Internet, and the technology sector evolves so quickly.  It&rsquo;s
amazing that the law the deceased was being prosecuted under, pertaining
to computers, is from
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Fraud_and_Abuse_Act">1986</a>.  Can
you even remember what computers were like in 1986?  I didn&rsquo;t even
exist!  My first family computer ran Windows 95.  I can only imagine how
archaic laws would be that were based on such rapidly evolving tech.</p>

<p>The limiting of information is problematic to me.  How do the people of
China, Iran, and others feel about their government?  I assume they are
aware that the government is limiting their body of knowledge.  Even the
US television news agencies can&rsquo;t get the story straight.  It
reminds me of George Orwell&rsquo;s <em>1984</em>, where the language is limited to
curtail expression.  If the free world uses the Internet as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transactive_memory">Transactive Memory</a>, does the
oppressed world know what they&rsquo;re missing?  Can you know what you&rsquo;re
missing, before you&rsquo;ve lost it?</p>

<p>The media and copyright lobby disgust me.  I&rsquo;m disgusted that <a href="http://www.mpaa.org/about/ceo">my former state senator</a>
is now the Chairman and
CEO of the MPAA.  Remember learning in high school civics the term
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revolving_door_%28politics%29">&ldquo;Revolving Door&rdquo;</a>? Case
in point.</p>

<p>America was constitutionalized as a republic, but through
amendment has <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic_republic">evolved</a>
into a democratic republic.  The idea of a republic was important to an
<a href="http://seattletimes.com/html/nationworld/2003332210_tuesday31.html">agrarian society</a>,
and we still feel the effects every first Tuesday in
November; the least convenient day of the week.  Voting for someone
just to represent you was convenient when your form of long-range
communication was a man on a pony.  With the rise of the Internet, and
representatives who work for their lobbies and not the people,
why do we still elect officials?  Why are we a republic?  Why not just a
democracy?  Allow voters to authenticate and cast their vote online.
Everyone.  No computer or internet?  I&rsquo;m sure your local library offers
both free for public use.  &ldquo;But people don&rsquo;t always know what&rsquo;s right.&rdquo;
Sure, I think some people aren&rsquo;t too bright.  But then I see the
deadlock in congress, fiscal cliff after fiscal cliff, and I can&rsquo;t help
but think we could do better if we just fired all of these assholes.</p>

<p>Why can&rsquo;t the difference in viewpoints be celebrated?  A good leader
recognizes both sides of the coin.  I love having a diverse team of
people with varying backgrounds, because they come up with solutions I
never could have.  And if you want to beat your enemy, you have to know
your enemy.  That means empathizing, understanding where they come from.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>If you give orders and explain nothing, you might get obedience, but<br/>you&rsquo;ll get no creativity. If you tell them your purpose, then when your<br/>original plan is shown to be faulty, they&rsquo;ll find another way to achieve<br/>your goal. Explaining to your men doesn&rsquo;t weaken their respect for you,<br/>it proves your respect for them.</p><footer><strong>Han Tzu</strong> <cite>Shadow of the Giant Pg. 303 by Orson Scott Card</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t hate anyone for what they believe, nor do I
try to persuade them otherwise.  I just feel like the technologically
minded are under represented in Washington.  I wish we had a
technological party.  We need a
party that strives to protect the internet, the ideals behind
the freedom and preservation of information, the technical investment in
sovereign energy and our failing infrastructure, and internet access
speeds that are unrivaled in the world, not stagnated by corporations
who are relatively regional monopolies.  One where social
issues are open to debate, but also where protecting our greatest asset and
achievement is top priority.  One where the media industry is invited to
the table, unlike the back door <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Online_Piracy_Act">policies</a>
they would try to slip in under our noses.  My dad advocated a turn the
other cheek policy.  That&rsquo;s called acting like an adult.</p>

<p>My belief of good vs. evil is that there is no good or evil, but that people
are inherently selfish.  They
do things that are perceived by others as evil.  But they don&rsquo;t do
things because those actions are evil, they do them because they gain
some form of personal utility from the action; they perceive the action
as good.  And it is good&hellip;to them.  It&rsquo;s easy to be evil.  It&rsquo;s the easy
way out.  It&rsquo;s harder to think about other people.  It&rsquo;s tougher to do
the right thing.  Being good is so recognizably hard; it&rsquo;s impressive.</p>

<p>The president of MIT, L. Rafael Reif, had this to say regarding the
deceased: <a href="http://touch.latimes.com/#section/-1/article/p2p-74009443/">&ldquo;It pains me to think that MIT played any role in a series of events that have ended in tragedy&hellip;&rdquo;</a>
Fuck you. Maybe if MIT&rsquo;s bottom line wasn&rsquo;t their acceptance rate, they
might be able to look out for more than just their own.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>All that is necessary for the triumph of evil is that good men do<br/>nothing.</p><footer><strong>Edmund Burke</strong> <cite>Thoughts on the Cause of Present Discontents</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Suicide is never the answer.  No matter how shitty your current
situation is, no matter if things will never go back to the way they
were, you will always be able to change your situation.  Maybe not
immediately, but that&rsquo;s what goals are for.  Anyone who ever committed
suicide to prove a point could have done more for their cause dedicating
the rest of their life to it.  If you&rsquo;re feeling depressed, talk to
someone.  It will make you feel so much better to talk to someone about
what&rsquo;s upsetting you.  As much as people like to shit on the Catholic
Church, I feel like the Catholic practice of penance (confession),
provides a cathartic placebo effect.  If you are depressed or hurting, and
you need someone to talk to, even a complete stranger, feel free to
contact me.  I will always provide an ear and a shoulder.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It seems strange that my life should end in such a terrible place, but<br/>for three years I had roses and apologized to no one. I shall die here.<br/>Every inch of me shall perish. Every inch, but one. An inch. It is small<br/>and it is fragile and it is the only thing in the world worth having. We<br/>must never lose it or give it away. We must NEVER let them take it from<br/>us. I hope that whoever you are, you escape this place. I hope that the<br/>world turns, and that things get better. But what I hope most of all is<br/>that you understand what I mean when I tell you that, even though I do<br/>not know you, and even though I may never meet you, laugh with you, cry<br/>with you, or kiss you, I love you. With all my heart, I love you.</p><footer><strong>Valerie</strong> <cite>V for Vendetta</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The next time the media industry tries to limit what you have access to
on the Internet, make a big ruckus.  Inform everyone you know about the
facts.  Pushing for an increase in media piracy activities is not the
right answer.  Instead we should push to boycott working for
organizations like the RIAA and MPAA and their ilk.  Think about how
much better off we would be in the United States if teachers were paid
like rock stars and rock stars were paid like teachers?  Instead, everyone
in the media industry needs a fat paycheck.  Celebrity is the case in
point of the blind leading the blind.  Did you know that EMI
<a href="https://mashable.com/2013/01/18/i-have-a-dream-internet-freedom/">owns</a>
the copyright to the footage of Martin Luther King&rsquo;s &ldquo;I have a
dream&rdquo; speech?  If you can find it, I bet it wont be up long.  Frankly,
I&rsquo;m surprised EMI doesn&rsquo;t also own the Declaration of Independence and
Constitution, charging admission.</p>

<p>Revolutions are a continuation of the battle between sword and shield.
Something new is created and shows potential, then doubters pop up
seeking to curtail that which upsets their competitive edge.  In the
case of information, many make money and become powerful off
limiting the access to knowledge.  I think all knowledge that is
beneficial to mankind should be open, and that the Internet is the ultimate
utility for the sharing of our collective knowledge.  Where do you draw
the line, you might ask?  I think the knowledge required to make atomic
weapons and 3D-print receivers is decidedly unbefitting of society,
for instance.
And in the end, you can&rsquo;t take any of the knowledge you protect with
you.  If everyone shared what they knew, then you&rsquo;d have a more
improved life, since then the right people would be
in the know to advance our being.  Technology would advance even faster
than it does currently if we weren&rsquo;t limited to
<a href="http://www.techradar.com/us/news/computing-components/processors/why-intels-new-cpus-disappoint-1077260">tick-tock</a> product
cycles and business secrets.</p>

<p>So what does a rant about government, antiquated laws, corrupt
representatives, celebrating diversity, hypothetical political parties,
inaction, and established industries have to do with anything?
They&rsquo;re all anchored to a suicide.  They&rsquo;re all that&rsquo;s been running
through my mind lately.  What I see in the deceased, I see in myself.
Standing amongst my peers, celebrating <a href="http://www.internetfreedomday.net/">Internet Freedom Day</a>
, listening to <a href="https://www.eff.org/about/staff/peter-eckersley">Peter Eckersley</a> of the
<a href="https://www.eff.org/">EFF</a> talk, I realized <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vo0D6bzxLLw">&lsquo;The power is
yours!&rsquo;</a>.
So now I add my voice to the or so 20 Internet activists that will continue to
spring up as one falls.</p>

<p>What will you do to shape the world you live in?  What are you going to do to
fix it?  If you don&rsquo;t, I will.  Because if you want something done
right, you have to do it yourself.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It has to start somewhere It has to start sometime<br/>What better place than here, what better time than now?</p><footer><strong>Rage Against the Machine</strong> <cite>Guerrilla Radio</cite></footer></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
