<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ARM on Nick Desaulniers</title><link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/categories/arm/</link><description>Recent content in ARM on Nick Desaulniers</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 11:39:11 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/categories/arm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Disambiguating Arm, Arm ARM, Armv9, ARM9, ARM64, AArch64, A64, A78, ...</title><link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2023/03/10/disambiguating-arm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 11:39:11 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2023/03/10/disambiguating-arm/</guid><description>If you&amp;rsquo;re new to the Arm ecosystem, consider this a quick primer on terms you likely have seen before but might have questions about.
The Arm architecture is a family of Reduced Instruction Set Architectures (RISC) with simple addressing modes. Data processing is done on register operands otherwise relying on loads and stores to move data into and out of registers.
Arm Limited, the British company, stewards the Arm architecture.</description></item><item><title>Cross Compiling C/C++ for Android</title><link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/07/01/android-cli/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/07/01/android-cli/</guid><description>Let’s say you want to build a hello world command line application in C or C++ and run it on your Android phone. How would you go about it? It’s not super practical; apps visible and distributable to end users must use the framework (AFAIK), but for folks looking to get into developing on ARM it’s likely they have an ARM device in their pocket.
This post is for folks who typically invoke their compiler from the command line, either explicitly, from build scripts, or other forms of automation.</description></item></channel></rss>