<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: C++ | Nick Desaulniers]]></title>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/categories/c-plus-plus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-24T22:32:52-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Desaulniers]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static and Dynamic Libraries]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/11/20/static-and-dynamic-libraries/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-20T23:55:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/11/20/static-and-dynamic-libraries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second post in a series on memory segmentation.  It covers working
with static and dynamic libraries in Linux and OSX.  Make sure to check out the
<a href="/blog/2016/08/13/object-files-and-symbols/">first on object files and symbols</a>.</p>

<p>Let’s say we wanted to reuse some of the code from our previous project in our
next one.  We could continue to copy around object files, but let’s say we have
a bunch and it’s hard to keep track of all of them.  Let’s combine multiple
object files into an archive or static library.  Similar to a more conventional
zip file or &ldquo;compressed archive,&rdquo; our static library will be an uncompressed
archive.</p>

<p>We can use the <code>ar</code> command to create and manipulate a static archive.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ clang -c x.c y.c
$ ar -rv libhello.a x.o y.o
</code></p>

<p>The <code>-r</code> flag will create the archive named <code>libhello.a</code> and add the files
<code>x.o</code> and <code>y.o</code> to its index.  I like to add the <code>-v</code> flag for verbose output.
Then we can use the familiar <code>nm</code> tool I introduced in the
<a href="/blog/2016/08/13/object-files-and-symbols/">previous post</a>
to examine the content of the archives and their symbols.</p>

<p>```sh
$ file libhello.a
libhello.a: current ar archive random library
$ nm libhello.a
libhello.a(x.o):</p>

<pre><code>             U _puts
</code></pre>

<p>0000000000000000 T _x</p>

<p>libhello.a(y.o):</p>

<pre><code>             U _puts
</code></pre>

<p>0000000000000000 T _y
```</p>

<p>Some other useful flags for <code>ar</code> are <code>-d</code> to delete an object file, ex. <code>ar -d
libhello.a y.o</code> and <code>-u</code> to update existing members of the archive when their
source and object files are updated.  Not only can we run <code>nm</code> on our archive,
<code>otool</code> and <code>objdump</code> both work.</p>

<p>Now that we have our static library, we can statically link it to our program
and see the resulting symbols.  The <code>.a</code> suffix is typical on both OSX and
Linux for archive files.</p>

<p>```sh
$ clang main.o libhello.a
$ nm a.out
0000000100000f30 T _main</p>

<pre><code>             U _puts
</code></pre>

<p>0000000100000f50 T <em>x
0000000100000f70 T </em>y
```</p>

<p>Our compiler understands how to index into archive files and pull out the
functions it needs to combine into the final executable.  If we use a static
library to statically link all functions required, we can have one binary with
no dependencies.  This can make deployment of binaries simple, but also greatly
increase their size.  Upgrading large binaries incrementally becomes more
costly in terms of space.</p>

<p>While static libraries allowed us to reuse source code, static linkage does not
allow us to reuse memory for executable code between different processes.  I
really want to put off talking about memory benefits until the next post, but
know that the solution to this problem lies in &ldquo;dynamic libraries.&rdquo;</p>

<p>While having a single binary file keeps things simple, it can really hamper
memory sharing and incremental relinking.  For example, if you have multiple
executables that are all built with the same static library, unless your OS is
really smart about copy-on-write page sharing, then you’re likely loading
multiple copies of the same exact code into memory! What a waste!  Also, when
you want to rebuild or update your binary, you spend time performing relocation
again and again with static libraries.  What if we could set aside object files
that we could share amongst multiple instances of the same or even different
processes, and perform relocation at runtime?</p>

<p>The solution is known as dynamic libraries.  If static libraries and static
linkage were Atari controllers, dynamic libraries and dynamic linkage are Steel
Battalion controllers.  We’ll show how to work with them in the rest of this
post, but I’ll prove how memory is saved in a later post.</p>

<p>Let’s say we want to created a shared version of libhello.  Dynamic libraries
typically have different suffixes per OS since each OS has it’s preferred
object file format.  On Linux the .so suffix is common, .dylib on OSX, and .dll
on Windows.</p>

<p>```sh
$ clang -shared -fpic x.c y.c -o libhello.dylib
$ file libhello.dylib
libhello.dylib: Mach-O 64-bit dynamically linked shared library x86_64
$ nm libhello.dylib</p>

<pre><code>             U _puts
</code></pre>

<p>0000000000000f50 T <em>x
0000000000000f70 T </em>y
```</p>

<p>The <code>-shared</code> flag tells the linker to create a special file called a shared
library.  The <code>-fpic</code> option converts absolute addresses to relative addresses,
which allows for different processes to load the library at different virtual
addresses and share memory.</p>

<p>Now that we have our shared library, let’s dynamically link it into our
executable.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ clang main.c libhello.dylib
$ ./a.out
x
y
</code></p>

<p>The dynamic linker essential produces an incomplete binary.  You can verify
with <code>nm</code>.  At runtime, we’ll delay start up to perform some memory mapping
early on in the process start (performed by the dynamic linker) and pay slight
costs for trampolining into position independent code.</p>

<p>Let’s say we want to know what dynamic libraries a binary is using.  You can
either query the executable (most executable object file formats contain a
header the dynamic linker will parse and pull in libs) or observe the
executable while running it.  Because each major OS has its own object file
format, they each have their own tools for these two checks.  Note that
statically linked libraries won’t show up here, since their object code has
already been linked in and thus we’re not able to differentiate between object
code that came from our first party code vs third party static libraries.</p>

<p>On OSX, we can use <code>otool -L &lt;bin&gt;</code> to check which .dylibs will get pulled in.</p>

<p>```sh
$ otool -L a.out
a.out:</p>

<pre><code>       libhello.dylib (compatibility version 0.0.0, current version 0.0.0)
       /usr/lib/libSystem.B.dylib (compatibility version 1.0.0, current version 1226.10.1)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>So we can see that <code>a.out</code> depends on <code>libhello.dylib</code> (and expects to find it
in the same directory as <code>a.out</code>).  It also depends on shared library called
libSystem.B.dylib.  If you run <code>otool -L</code> on libSystem itself, you’ll see it
depends on a bunch of other libraries including a C runtime, malloc
implementation, pthreads implementation, and more.  Let’s say you want to find
the final resting place of where a symbol is defined, without digging with <code>nm</code>
and <code>otool</code>, you can fire up your trusty debugger and ask it.</p>

<p>```sh
$ lldb a.out
&hellip;
(lldb) image lookup -r -s puts
&hellip;</p>

<pre><code>    Summary: libsystem_c.dylib`puts        Address: libsystem_c.dylib[0x0000000000085c30] (libsystem_c.dylib.__TEXT.__stubs + 3216)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>You’ll see a lot of output since <code>puts</code> is treated as a regex.  You’re looking
for the Summary line that has an address and is <strong>not</strong> a symbol stub.  You can
then check your work with <code>otool</code> and <code>nm</code>.</p>

<p>If we want to observe the dynamic linker in action on OSX, we can use <code>dtruss</code>:</p>

<p><code>sh
$ sudo dtruss ./a.out
...
stat64("libhello.dylib\0", 0x7FFF50CEAC68, 0x1)         = 0 0
open("libhello.dylib\0", 0x0, 0x0)              = 3 0
...
mmap(0x10EF27000, 0x1000, 0x5, 0x12, 0x3, 0x0)          = 0x10EF27000 0
mmap(0x10EF28000, 0x1000, 0x3, 0x12, 0x3, 0x1000)               = 0x10EF28000 0
mmap(0x10EF29000, 0xC0, 0x1, 0x12, 0x3, 0x2000)         = 0x10EF29000 0
...
close(0x3)              = 0 0
...
</code></p>

<p>On Linux, we can simply use <code>ldd</code> or <code>readelf -d</code> to query an executable for a
list of its dynamic libraries.</p>

<p>```sh
$ clang -shared -fpic x.c y.c -o libhello.so
$ clang main.c libhello.so
$ ldd a.out</p>

<pre><code>       linux-vdso.so.1 =&gt;  (0x00007fff95d43000)
       libhello.so =&gt; not found
       libc.so.6 =&gt; /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libc.so.6 (0x00007fcc98c5f000)
       /lib64/ld-linux-x86-64.so.2 (0x0000555993852000)
</code></pre>

<p>$ readelf -d a.out
Dynamic section at offset 0xe18 contains 25 entries:
  Tag        Type                         Name/Value
 0x0000000000000001 (NEEDED)             Shared library: [libhello.so]
 0x0000000000000001 (NEEDED)             Shared library: [libc.so.6]
&hellip;
```</p>

<p>We can then use <code>strace</code> to observe the dynamic linker in action on Linux:</p>

<p><code>sh
$ LD_LIBRARY_PATH=. strace ./a.out
...
open("./libhello.so", O_RDONLY|O_CLOEXEC) = 3
...
read(3, "\177ELF\2\1\1\0\0\0\0\0\0\0\0\0\3\0&gt;\0\1\0\0\0\260\5\0\0\0\0\0\0"..., 832) = 832
fstat(3, {st_mode=S_IFREG|0755, st_size=8216, ...}) = 0
close(3)                                = 0
...
</code></p>

<p>What’s this <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code> thing?  That’s shell syntax for setting an
environmental variable just for the duration of that command (as opposed to
exporting it so it stays set for multiple commands).  As opposed to OSX’s
dynamic linker, which was happy to look in the cwd for libhello.dylib, on Linux
we must supply the cwd if the dynamic library we want to link in is not in the
standard search path.</p>

<p>But what is the standard search path?  Well, there’s another environmental
variable we can set to see this, <code>LD_DEBUG</code>.  For example, on OSX:</p>

<p>```sh
$ LD_DEBUG=libs LD_LIBRARY_PATH=. ./a.out</p>

<pre><code> 15828:        find library=libhello.so [0]; searching
 15828:         search path=./tls/x86_64:./tls:./x86_64:.             (LD_LIBRARY_PATH)
 15828:          trying file=./tls/x86_64/libhello.so
 15828:          trying file=./tls/libhello.so
 15828:          trying file=./x86_64/libhello.so
 15828:          trying file=./libhello.so
 15828:
 15828:        find library=libc.so.6 [0]; searching
 15828:         search path=./tls/x86_64:./tls:./x86_64:.             (LD_LIBRARY_PATH)
 15828:          trying file=./tls/x86_64/libc.so.6
 1earc:          trying file=./tls/libc.so.6
 15828:          trying file=./x86_64/libc.so.6
 15828:          trying file=./libc.so.6
 15828:         search cache=/etc/ld.so.cache
 15828:          trying file=/lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libc.so.6
 15828:        calling init: /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libc.so.6
 15828:        calling init: ./libhello.so
 15828:        initialize program: ./a.out
 15828:        transferring control: ./a.out
</code></pre>

<p>x
y</p>

<pre><code> 15828:        calling fini: ./a.out [0]
 15828:        calling fini: ./libhello.so [0]
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><code>LD_DEBUG</code> is pretty useful.  Try:</p>

<p>```sh
$ LD_DEBUG=help ./a.out
Valid options for the LD_DEBUG environment variable are:</p>

<p>  libs        display library search paths
  reloc       display relocation processing
  files       display progress for input file
  symbols     display symbol table processing
  bindings    display information about symbol binding
  versions    display version dependencies
  scopes      display scope information
  all         all previous options combined
  statistics  display relocation statistics
  unused      determined unused DSOs
  help        display this help message and exit</p>

<p>To direct the debugging output into a file instead of standard output
a filename can be specified using the LD_DEBUG_OUTPUT environment variable.
<code>``
For some cool stuff, I recommend checking out</code>LD_DEBUG=symbols<code>and
</code>LD_DEBUG=statistics`.</p>

<p>Going back to <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code>, usually libraries you create and want to reuse
between projects go into /usr/local/lib and the headers into
/usr/local/include.  I think of the convention as:</p>

<p>```sh
$ tree -L 2 /usr/
/usr
├── bin # system installed binaries like nm, gcc
├── include # system installed headers like stdio.h
├── lib # system installed libraries, both static and dynamic
└── local</p>

<pre><code>├── bin # user installed binaries like rustc
├── include # user installed headers
└── lib # user installed
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Unfortunately, it’s a loose convention that’s broken down over the years and
things are scattered all over the place.  You can also run into dependency and
versioning issues, that I don’t want to get into here, by placing libraries
here instead of keeping them in-tree or out-of-tree of the source code of a
project.  Just know when you see a library like <code>libc.so.6</code> that the numeric
suffix is a major version number that follows semantic versioning.  For more
information, you should read Michael Kerrisk’s excellent book <em>The Linux
Programming Interface</em>.  This post is based on his chapter’s 41 &amp; 42 (but with
more info on tooling and OSX).</p>

<p>If we were to place our libhello.so into /usr/local/lib (on Linux you need to
then run <code>sudo ldconfig</code>) and move x.h and y.h to /usr/local/include, then we
could then compile with:</p>

<p><code>sh
$ clang main.c -lhello
</code></p>

<p>Note that rather than give a full path to our library, we can use the <code>-l</code> flag
followed by the name of our library with the lib prefix and .so suffix removed.</p>

<p>When working with shared libraries and external code, three flags I use pretty
often:</p>

<p><code>
* -l&lt;libname to link, no lib prefix or file extension; ex: -lnanomsg to link libnanomsg.so&gt;
* -L &lt;path to search for lib if in non standard directory&gt;
* -I &lt;path to headers for that library, if in non standard directory&gt;
</code></p>

<p>For finding specific flags needed for compilation where dynamic linkage is
required, a tool called <code>pkg-config</code> can be used for finding appropriate flags.
I’ve had less than stellar experiences with the tool as it puts the onus on the
library author to maintain the .pc files, and the user to have them installed
in the right place that <code>pkg-config</code> looks.  When they do exist and are
installed properly, the tool works well:</p>

<p><code>sh
$ sudo apt-get install libpng12-dev
$ pkg-config --libs --cflags libpng12
-I/usr/include/libpng12  -lpng12
$ clang program.c `!!`
</code></p>

<p>Using another neat environmental variable, we can hook into the dynamic linkage
process and inject our own shared libraries to be linked instead of the
expected libraries.  Let’s say libgood.so and libmalicous.so both define a
symbol for a function (the same symbol name and function signature).  We can
get a binary that links in libgood.so’s function to instead call
libmalicous.so’s version:</p>

<p><code>sh
$ ./a.out
hello from libgood
$ LD_PRELOAD=./libmalicious.so ./a.out
hello from libmalicious
</code></p>

<p>LD_PRELOAD is not available on OSX, instead you can use
<code>DYLD_INSERT_LIBRARIES</code>, <code>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH</code>, and recompile the original
executable with <code>-flat_namespace</code>. Having to recompile the original executable
is less than ideal for hooking an existing binary, but I could not hook libc
as in the previous libmalicious example.  I would be interested to know if you
can though!</p>

<p>Manually invoking the dynamic linker from our code,
<a href="https://rafalcieslak.wordpress.com/2013/04/02/dynamic-linker-tricks-using-ld_preload-to-cheat-inject-features-and-investigate-programs/">we can even man in the middle library calls (call our hooked function first, then invoke the original target)</a>.
We’ll see more of this in the next post on using the dynamic linker.</p>

<p>As you can guess, readjusting the search paths for dynamic libraries is a
security concern as it let’s good and bad folks change the expected execution
paths.  Guarding against the use of these env vars becomes a rabbit hole that
gets pretty tricky to solve without the heavy handed use of statically linking
dependencies.</p>

<p>In the the previous post, I alluded to undefined symbols like <code>puts</code>.  <code>puts</code>
is part of libc, which is probably the most shared dynamic library on most
computing devices since most every program makes use of the C runtime.  (I
think of a “runtime” as implicit code that runs in your program that you didn’t
necessarily write yourself.  Usually a runtime is provided as a library that
gets implicitly linked into your executable when you compile.)  You can
statically link against libc with the <code>-static</code> flag, on Linux at least (OSX
makes this difficult,
<a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/content/qa/qa1118/_index.html">&ldquo;Apple does not support statically linked binaries on Mac OS X&rdquo;</a>).</p>

<p>I’m not sure what the benefit would be to mixing static and dynamic linking,
but after searching the search paths from LD_DEBUG=libs for shared versions of
a library, if any static ones are found, they will get linked in.</p>

<p>There’s also an interesting form of library called a &ldquo;virtual dynamic shared
object&rdquo; on Linux.  I haven’t covered memory mapping yet, but know it exists, is
usually hidden for libc, and that you can read more about it via <code>man 7 vdso</code>.</p>

<p>One thing I find interesting and don’t quite understand how to recreate is that
somehow glibc on Linux is also executable:</p>

<p>```sh
$ /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libc.so.6
GNU C Library (Ubuntu GLIBC 2.24-3ubuntu1) stable release version 2.24, by Roland McGrath et al.
Copyright &copy; 2016 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.
There is NO warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A
PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
Compiled by GNU CC version 6.2.0 20161005.
Available extensions:</p>

<pre><code>crypt add-on version 2.1 by Michael Glad and others
GNU Libidn by Simon Josefsson
Native POSIX Threads Library by Ulrich Drepper et al
BIND-8.2.3-T5B
</code></pre>

<p>libc ABIs: UNIQUE IFUNC
For bug reporting instructions, please see:
<a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/glibc/+bugs">https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/glibc/+bugs</a>.
```</p>

<p>Also, note that linking against third party code has licensing implications (of
course) of particular interest when it’s GPL or LGPL.
<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/10179181/1027966">Here is a good overview</a>
which I’d summarize as: code that <em>statically</em> links against LGPL code must
also be LGPL, while any form of linkage against GPL code must be GPL’d.</p>

<p>Ok, that was a lot. In the previous post, we covered
<a href="/blog/2016/08/13/object-files-and-symbols/">Object Files and Symbols</a>.
In this post we covered hacking around with static and dynamic linkage.  In the
next post, I hope to talk about manually invoking the dynamic linker at
runtime.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2016/08/13/object-files-and-symbols/">Part 1 &ndash; Object Files and Symbols</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2016/11/20/static-and-dynamic-libraries/">Part 2 &ndash; Static and Dynamic Libraries</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Object Files and Symbols]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/08/13/object-files-and-symbols/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-13T20:46:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/08/13/object-files-and-symbols</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What was supposed to be one blog post about memory segmentation turned into
what will be a series of posts.  As the first in the series, we cover the
extreme basics of object files and symbols.  In follow up posts, I
plan to talk about
<a href="/blog/2016/11/20/static-and-dynamic-libraries/">static libraries, dynamic libraries,</a>
dynamic linkage, memory segments, and finally memory usage accounting.  I also
cover command line tools for working with these notions, both in Linux and OSX.</p>

<p>A quick review of the compilation+execution pipeline (for terminology):</p>

<ol>
<li>Lexing produces tokens</li>
<li>Parsing produces an abstract syntax tree</li>
<li>Analysis produces a code flow graph</li>
<li>Optimization produces a reduced code flow graph</li>
<li>Code gen produces object code</li>
<li>Linkage produces a complete executable</li>
<li>Loader instructs the OS how to start running the executable</li>
</ol>


<p>This series will focus on part #6.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say you have some amazing C/C++ code,  but for separations of concerns,
you want to start moving it out into separate source files.  Whereas previously
in one file you had:</p>

<p>```c
// main.c</p>

<h1>include &lt;stdio.h></h1>

<p>void helper () {
  puts(&ldquo;helper&rdquo;);
}
int main () {
  helper();
}
```</p>

<p>You now have two source files and maybe a header:</p>

<p>```c
// main.c</p>

<h1>include &ldquo;helper.h&rdquo;</h1>

<p>int main () {
  helper();
}</p>

<p>// helper.h
void helper();</p>

<p>//helper.c</p>

<h1>include &lt;stdio.h></h1>

<h1>include &ldquo;helper.h&rdquo;</h1>

<p>void helper () {
  puts(&ldquo;helper&rdquo;);
}
```</p>

<p>In the single source version, we would have compiled and linked that with
<code>clang main.c</code> and had an executable file.  In the multiple source version, we
first compile our source files to object files, then link them altogether.
That can be done separately:</p>

<p><code>sh
$ clang -c helper.c     # produces helper.o
$ clang -c main.c       # produces main.o
$ clang main.o helper.o # produces a.out
</code></p>

<p>We can also do the compilation and linkage in one step:</p>

<p><code>sh
$ clang helper.c main.c # produces a.out
</code></p>

<p>Nothing special thus far; C/C++ 101.  In the first case of separate compilation
and linkage steps, we were left with intermediate object files (.o).  What
exactly are these?</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object_file">Object files</a>
are almost full executables.  They contain machine code, but that code still
requires a relocation step.  It also contains metadata about the addresses of
its variables and functions (called symbols) in an associative data structure
called a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbol_table">symbol table</a>.
The addresses may not be the final address of the symbol in the final
executable. They also contain some information for the loader and probably some
other stuff.</p>

<p>Remember that if we fail to specify the helper object file, we&rsquo;ll get an
undefined symbol error.</p>

<p>```sh
$ clang main.c
Undefined symbols for architecture x86_64:
  &ldquo;_helper&rdquo;, referenced from:</p>

<pre><code>  _main in main-459dde.o
</code></pre>

<p>ld: symbol(s) not found for architecture x86_64
clang: error: linker command failed with exit code 1 (use -v to see invocation)
```</p>

<p>The problem is main.o refers to some symbol called <code>helper</code>, but on it&rsquo;s own
doesn&rsquo;t contain any more information about it.  Let&rsquo;s say we want to know what
symbols an object file contains, or expects to find elsewhere.  Let&rsquo;s introduce
our first tool, <code>nm</code>.  <code>nm</code> will print the name list or symbol table for a
given object or executable file.  On OSX, these are prefixed with an
underscore.</p>

<p>```sh
$ nm helper.o
0000000000000000 T _helper</p>

<pre><code>             U _puts
</code></pre>

<p>$ nm main.o</p>

<pre><code>             U _helper
</code></pre>

<p>0000000000000000 T _main</p>

<p>$ nm a.out
&hellip;
0000000100000f50 T <em>helper
0000000100000f70 T </em>main</p>

<pre><code>             U _puts
</code></pre>

<p>&hellip;
```</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s dissect what&rsquo;s going on here.  The output (as understood by <code>man 1 nm</code>)
is a space separated list of address, type, and symbol name.  We can see that
the addresses are placeholders in object files, and final in executables.  The
name should make sense; it&rsquo;s the name of the function or variable.  While I&rsquo;d
love to get in depth on the various symbol types and talk about sections, I
don&rsquo;t think I could do as great a job as Peter Van Der Linden in his book
&ldquo;Expert C Programming: Deep C Secrets.&rdquo;</p>

<p>For our case, we just care about whether the symbol in a given object file is
defined or not.  The type U (undefined) means that this symbol is referenced or
used in this object code/executable, but it&rsquo;s value wasn&rsquo;t defined here.
When we compiled main.c alone and got the undefined symbol error, it should now
make sense why we got the undefined symbol error for helper.  main.o contains
a symbol for main, and references helper.  helper.o contains a symbol for
helper, and references to puts.  The final executable contains symbols for main
and helper and references to puts.</p>

<p>You might be wondering where puts comes from then, and why didn&rsquo;t we get an
undefined symbol error for puts like we did earlier for helper.  The answer is
the C runtime.  libc is implicitly dynamically linked to all executables
created by the C compiler.  We&rsquo;ll cover dynamic linkage in a later post in
this series.</p>

<p>When the linker performs relocation on the object files, combining them into a
final executable, it goes through placeholders of addresses and fills them in.
We did this manually in our post on
<a href="/blog/2015/05/25/interpreter-compiler-jit/">JIT compilers</a>.</p>

<p>While <code>nm</code> gave us a look into our symbol table, two other tools I use
frequently are <code>objdump</code> on Linux and <code>otool</code> on OSX.  Both of these provide
disassembled assembly instructions and their addresses.  Note how the symbols
for functions get translated into labels of the disassembled functions, and
that their address points to the first instruction in that label.  Since I&rsquo;ve
shown <code>objdump</code>
<a href="/blog/2013/04/03/basic-jit/">numerous times</a>
in
<a href="/blog/2014/04/18/lets-write-some-x86-64/">previous posts</a>,
here&rsquo;s <code>otool</code>.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ otool -tV helper.o
helper.o:
(__TEXT,__text) section
_helper:
0000000000000000    pushq    %rbp
0000000000000001    movq    %rsp, %rbp
0000000000000004    subq    $0x10, %rsp
0000000000000008    leaq    0xe(%rip), %rdi         ## literal pool for: "helper"
000000000000000f    callq    _puts
0000000000000014    movl    %eax, -0x4(%rbp)
0000000000000017    addq    $0x10, %rsp
000000000000001b    popq    %rbp
000000000000001c    retq
$ otool -tV main.o
main.o:
(__TEXT,__text) section
_main:
0000000000000000    pushq    %rbp
0000000000000001    movq    %rsp, %rbp
0000000000000004    movb    $0x0, %al
0000000000000006    callq    _helper
000000000000000b    xorl    %eax, %eax
000000000000000d    popq    %rbp
000000000000000e    retq
$ otool -tV a.out
a.out:
(__TEXT,__text) section
_helper:
0000000100000f50    pushq    %rbp
0000000100000f51    movq    %rsp, %rbp
0000000100000f54    subq    $0x10, %rsp
0000000100000f58    leaq    0x43(%rip), %rdi        ## literal pool for: "helper"
0000000100000f5f    callq    0x100000f80             ## symbol stub for: _puts
0000000100000f64    movl    %eax, -0x4(%rbp)
0000000100000f67    addq    $0x10, %rsp
0000000100000f6b    popq    %rbp
0000000100000f6c    retq
0000000100000f6d    nop
0000000100000f6e    nop
0000000100000f6f    nop
_main:
0000000100000f70    pushq    %rbp
0000000100000f71    movq    %rsp, %rbp
0000000100000f74    movb    $0x0, %al
0000000100000f76    callq    _helper
0000000100000f7b    xorl    %eax, %eax
0000000100000f7d    popq    %rbp
0000000100000f7e    retq
</code></p>

<p><code>readelf -s &lt;object file&gt;</code> will give us a list of symbols on Linux.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Executable_and_Linkable_Format">ELF</a>
is the file format used by the loader on Linux, while OSX uses
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mach-O">Mach-O</a>.
Thus <code>readelf</code> and <code>otool</code>, respectively.</p>

<p>Also note that for static linkage, symbols need to be unique*, as they refer to
memory locations to either read/write to in the case of variables or locations
to jump to in the case of functions.</p>

<p>```sh
$ cat double_define.c
void a () {}
void a () {}
int main () {}
$ clang double_define.c
double_define.c:2:6: error: redefinition of &lsquo;a&rsquo;
void a () {}</p>

<pre><code> ^
</code></pre>

<p>double_define.c:1:6: note: previous definition is here
void a () {}</p>

<pre><code> ^
</code></pre>

<p>1 error generated.
```</p>

<p>*: there&rsquo;s a notion of weak symbols, and some special things for dynamic
libraries we&rsquo;ll see in a follow up post.</p>

<p>Languages like C++ that support function overloading (functions with the same
name but different arguments, return types, namespaces, or class) must mangle
their function names to make them unique.</p>

<p>Code like:
```c++
namespace util {
  class Widget {</p>

<pre><code>public:
  void doSomething (bool save);
  void doSomething (int n);
</code></pre>

<p>  };
}
<code>
Will produce symbols like:
</code>sh
$ clang class.cpp -std=c++11
$ nm a.out
0000000100000f70 T <strong>ZN4util6Widget11doSomethingEb
0000000100000f60 T </strong>ZN4util6Widget11doSomethingEi
&hellip;
<code>
Note: GNU `nm` on Linux distros will have a `--demangle` option:
</code>sh
$ nm &mdash;demangle a.out
&hellip;
00000000004006d0 T util::Widget::doSomething(bool)
00000000004006a0 T util::Widget::doSomething(int)
&hellip;
<code>
On OSX, we can pipe `nm` into `c++filt`:
</code>sh
$ nm a.out | c++filt
0000000100000f70 T util::Widget::doSomething(bool)
0000000100000f60 T util::Widget::doSomething(int)
&hellip;
<code>``
Finally, if you don't have an object file, but instead a backtrace that needs
demangling, you can either invoke</code>c++filt` manually or use
<a href="http://demangler.com/">demangler.com</a>.</p>

<p>Rust also mangles its function names.  For FFI or interface with C functions,
other languages usually have to look for or expose symbols in a manner suited
to C, the lowest common denominator.
<a href="http://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/language/language_linkage">C++</a>
has <code>extern "C"</code> blocks and
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ffi.html">Rust</a>
has <code>extern</code> blocks.</p>

<p>We can use <code>strip</code> to remove symbols from a binary.  This can slim down a
binary at the cost of making stack traces unreadable.  If you&rsquo;re following
along at home, try comparing the output from your disassembler and <code>nm</code> before
and after running <code>strip</code> on the executable.  Luckily, you can&rsquo;t strip the
symbols out of object files, otherwise they&rsquo;d be useless as you&rsquo;d no longer be
able to link them.</p>

<p>If we compile with the <code>-g</code> flag, we can create a different kind of symbol;
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debug_symbol">debug symbols</a>.
Depending on your compiler+host OS, you&rsquo;ll get another file you can run through
<code>nm</code> to see an entry per symbol.  You&rsquo;ll get more info by using <code>dwarfdump</code> on
this file.  Debug symbols will retain source information such as filename and
line number for all symbols.</p>

<p>This post should have been a simple refresher of some of the basics of working
with C code. Finding symbols to be placed into a final executable and
relocating addresses are the main job of the linker, and will be the main theme
of the posts in this series. Keep your eyes out for more in this series on
memory segmentation.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2016/08/13/object-files-and-symbols/">Part 1 &ndash; Object Files and Symbols</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2016/11/20/static-and-dynamic-libraries/">Part 2 &ndash; Static and Dynamic Libraries</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cross Compiling C/C++ for Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/07/01/android-cli/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-01T22:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/07/01/android-cli</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s say you want to build a hello world command line application in C or C++
and run it on your Android phone.  How would you go about it?  It’s not super
practical; apps visible and distributable to end users must use the framework
(AFAIK), but for folks looking to get into developing on ARM it’s likely they
have an ARM device in their pocket.</p>

<p>This post is for folks who typically invoke their compiler from the command
line, either explicitly, from build scripts, or other forms of automation.</p>

<p>At
<a href="https://twitter.com/LostOracle/status/697859368226697218">work</a>,
when working on Android, we typically checkout the entire Android source code
(<a href="https://twitter.com/LostOracle/status/702569487531249664">which is huge</a>),
use <code>lunch</code> to configure a ton of environmental variables, then use Makefiles
with lots of includes and special vars.  We don’t want to spend the time and
disk space checking out the Android source code just to have a working cross
compiler.  Luckily, the Android tools team has an excellent utility to grab a
prebuilt cross compiler.</p>

<p>This assumes you’re building from a Linux host.  Android is a distribution of
Linux, which is much easier to target from a Linux host.  At home, I’ll usually
develop on my OSX machine, ssh’d into my headless Linux box. (iTerm2 and tmux
both have exclusive features, but I currently prefer iTerm2.)</p>

<p>The first thing we want to do is fetch the
<a href="https://developer.android.com/ndk/downloads/index.html">Android NDK</a>.
Not the SDK, the NDK.</p>

<p><code>sh
➜  ~ curl -O \
  http://dl.google.com/android/repository/android-ndk-r12b-linux-x86_64.zip
➜  ~ unzip android-ndk-r12b-linux-x86_64.zip
</code></p>

<p>It would be helpful to install adb and fastboot, too.  This might be different
for your distro’s package manager.  Better yet may be to just build from
source.</p>

<p><code>sh
➜  ~ sudo apt-get install android-tools-adb android-tools-fastboot
</code></p>

<p>Now for you Android device that you want to target, you’ll want to know the
ISA.  Let’s say I want to target my Nexus 6P, which has an ARMv8-A ISA (the
first 64b ARM ISA).</p>

<p><code>sh
➜  ~ ./android-ndk-r12b/build/tools/make_standalone_toolchain.py --arch arm64 \
  --install-dir ~/arm
</code></p>

<p>This will create a nice standalone bundle in <code>~/arm</code>.  It will contain our
cross compiler, linker, headers, libs, and
<a href="https://twitter.com/LostOracle/status/749297676223598592">sysroot (crt.o and friends)</a>.
Most Android devices are ARMv7-A, so you’d use <code>--arch arm</code>.  See the other
supported architectures for cross compiling under
<a href="https://developer.android.com/ndk/guides/standalone_toolchain.html#itc">table 4</a>.</p>

<p>You might also want to change your install-dir and possible add it to your
<code>$PATH</code>, or set <code>$CC</code> and <code>$CXX</code>.</p>

<p>Now we can compile <code>hello_world.c</code>.</p>

<p>```sh
➜  ~ cat hello_world.c</p>

<h1>include &lt;stdio.h></h1>

<p>int main () {
  puts(&ldquo;hello world&rdquo;);
}</p>

<p>➜  ~ ~/arm/bin/clang -pie hello_world.c
➜  ~ file a.out
a.out: ELF 64-bit LSB shared object, ARM aarch64, version 1 (SYSV), dynamically
linked, interpreter /system/bin/linker64,
BuildID[sha1]=ecc46648cf2c873253b3b522c0d14b91cf17c70f, not stripped
```</p>

<p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/30547603">Since Android Lollipop</a>,
Android has required that executables be linked as
position independent (<code>-pie</code>) to help provide
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Address_space_layout_randomization#Android">ASLR</a>.</p>

<p><code>&lt;install-dir&gt;/bin/</code> also has shell scripts with more full featured names like
<code>aarch64-linux-android-clang</code> if you prefer to have clearer named executables
in your $PATH.</p>

<p>Connect your phone, enable remote debugging, and accept the prompt for remote
debugging.</p>

<p><code>sh
➜  ~ adb push a.out /data/local/tmp/.
➜  ~ adb shell "./data/local/tmp/a.out"
hello world
</code></p>

<p>We’ll use this toolchain in a follow post to start writing some ARMv8-A
assembly.  Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Additional C/C++ Tooling]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2015/07/23/additional-c-slash-c-plus-plus-tooling/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-23T21:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2015/07/23/additional-c-slash-c-plus-plus-tooling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920025108.do">21st Century C by Ben Klemens</a>
was a great read. It had a section with an
intro to autotools, git, and gdb.
There are a few other useful tools that came to mind that I&rsquo;ve used when
working with C and C++ codebases. These tools are a great way to start
contributing to
<a href="https://github.com/nickdesaulniers/What-Open-Source-Means-To-Me#what-open-source-means-to-me">Open Source</a>
C &amp; C++ codebases; running these tools on
the code or adding them to the codebases.  A lot of these favor command line,
open source utilities. See how many you are familiar with!</p>

<h2>Build Tools</h2>

<h3>CMake</h3>

<p>The first tool I&rsquo;d like to take a look at is
<a href="http://www.cmake.org/overview/">CMake</a>.  CMake is yet another build tool; I
realize how contentious it is to even discuss one of the many.  From my
experience working with
<a href="https://kripken.github.io/emscripten-site/docs/introducing_emscripten/about_emscripten.html">Emscripten</a>,
we recommend the use of CMake for people
writing portable C/C++ programs.  CMake is able to emit Makefiles for unixes,
project files for Xcode on OSX, and project files for Visual Studio on Windows.
There are also a few other &ldquo;generators&rdquo; that you can use.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been really impressed with CMake&rsquo;s modules for
<a href="http://www.cmake.org/cmake/help/v3.0/command/find_package.html">finding dependencies</a>
and
<a href="http://www.cmake.org/cmake/help/v3.0/module/ExternalProject.html">another for fetching and building external dependencies</a>.
I think
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nshzjMDD79w">C++ needs a package manager badly</a>,
and I think CMake would be a solid foundation for one.</p>

<p>The syntax isn&rsquo;t the greatest, but when I wanted to try to build one of my C++
projects on Windows which I know nothing about developing on, I was able to
install CMake and Visual Studio and get my project building.  If you can build
your code on one platform, it will usually build on the others.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re not worried about writing cross platform C/C++, maybe CMake is not
worth the effort, but I find it useful.  I wrestle with the syntax sometimes,
but documentation is not bad and it&rsquo;s something you deal with early on in the
development of a project and hopefully never have to touch again (how I wish
that were true).</p>

<h2>Code Formatters</h2>

<h3>ClangFormat</h3>

<p>Another contentious point of concern amongst developers is code style.
<a href="http://google-styleguide.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/cppguide.html">Big companies</a>
with lots of C++ code have
<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/Developer_guide/Coding_Style#CC_practices">documents</a>
explaining their stylistic choices.  Don&rsquo;t waste another hour of your life
arguing about something that really doesn&rsquo;t matter.
<a href="http://clang.llvm.org/docs/ClangFormat.html">ClangFormat</a> will help you
codify your style and format your code for you to match the style.  Simply
write the code however you want, and run the formatter on it before commiting
it.</p>

<p>It can also emit a .clang-format file that you can commit and clang-format will automatically look for that file and use the rules codified there.</p>

<h2>Linters</h2>

<h3>Flint / Flint++</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/facebook/flint">Flint</a> is a C++ linter in use at Facebook.
Since it moved from being
implemented in C++ to D, I&rsquo;ve had issues building it.  I&rsquo;ve had better luck
with a fork that&rsquo;s pure C++ without any of the third party dependencies Flint
originally had, called
<a href="https://github.com/L2Program/FlintPlusPlus">Flint++</a>.  While not quite full-on
static analyzers, both can be used for finding potential issues in your code
ahead of time. Linters can look at individual files in isolation; you don&rsquo;t
have to wait for long recompiles like you would with a static analyzer.</p>

<h2>Static Analyzers</h2>

<h3>Scan-build</h3>

<p><a href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/scan-build.html">Scan-build</a> is a static
analyzer for C and C++ code.  You build your code &ldquo;through&rdquo; it, then use the
sibling tool scan-view to see the results.  Scan-view will emit and open an
html file that shows a list of the errors it detected.  It will insert
hyperlinks into the resulting document that step you through how certain
conditions could lead to a null pointer dereference, for example.  You can also
save and share those html files with others in the project. Static analyzers
will help you catch bugs at compile time before you run the code.</p>

<h2>Runtime Sanitizers</h2>

<h3>ASan and UBSan</h3>

<p>Clang&rsquo;s Address (ASan) and Undefined Behavior (UBSan) sanitizers are simply
compiler flags that can be used to detect errors at runtime.  ASan and UBSan
two of the more popular tools, but there are actually a ton and more being
implemented.  See the list
<a href="http://clang.llvm.org/docs/UsersManual.html#controlling-code-generation">here</a>.
These sanitizers will catch bugs at runtime, so you&rsquo;ll have to run the code
to notice any violations, at variable runtime performance costs per sanitizer.
ASan and TSan (Thread Sanitizer) made it into gcc4.8 and UBSan is in gcc4.9.</p>

<h2>Header Analysis</h2>

<h3>Include What You Use</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/include-what-you-use/include-what-you-use">Include What You Use</a>
(IWYU) helps you find unused or unnecessary <code>#include</code> preprocessor directives.
It should be obvious how this can help improve compile times. IWYU can also
help cut down on recompiles by recommending forward declarations under certain
conditions.
I look forward to the C++ module proposal being adopted, but until then this
tool can help you spot cruft that can be removed.</p>

<h2>Rapid Recompiles</h2>

<h3>ccache</h3>

<p><a href="https://ccache.samba.org/">ccache</a> greatly improves recompile times by caching
the results of parts of the compilation process.
<a href="https://github.com/nickdesaulniers/dotfiles/blob/49984b3e82022e5ce82e778fc8ce990f8e1e554a/.mozconfig#L1">I use when building Firefox</a>,
and it saves a great deal of time.</p>

<h3>distcc</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/distcc/distcc">distcc</a> is a distributed build system.
<a href="http://blog.dholbert.org/">Some folks at Mozilla</a> speed up their Firefox builds with it.</p>

<h2>Memory Leak Detectors</h2>

<h3>Valgrind</h3>

<p><a href="http://valgrind.org/info/about.html">Valgrind</a> has a
<a href="http://valgrind.org/info/about.html">suite of tools</a>, my
favorite being memcheck for finding memory leaks. Unfortunately, it doesn&rsquo;t
seem to work on OSX since 10.10.
<a href="https://code.google.com/p/address-sanitizer/wiki/ComparisonOfMemoryTools">This page</a>
referring to ASan seems to indicate that it can do everything Valgrind&rsquo;s
Memcheck can, at less of a runtime performance cost, but I&rsquo;m not sure how true
this is exactly.</p>

<h3>leaks</h3>

<p>A much more primitive tool for finding leaks from the command line, BSD&rsquo;s have
<code>leaks</code>.</p>

<p><code>bash
MallocStackLogging=1 ./a.out
leaks a.out
...
</code></p>

<h2>Profilers</h2>

<h3>Perf</h3>

<p>Perf, and
<a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/flamegraphs.html">Brendan Gregg&rsquo;s tools for emitting SVG flamegraphs</a>
from the output
are helpful for finding where time is spent in a program. In fact, there are
numerous perfomance analysis tools that are Linux specific.  My recommendation
is spend some time on <a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/linuxperf.html">Brendan Gregg&rsquo;s blog</a>.</p>

<h3>DTrace</h3>

<p>OSX doesn&rsquo;t have the same tooling as Linux, but DTrace was ported to it.  I&rsquo;ve
used it to find sampling profiles of my code before. Again,
<a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/dtrace.html">Brendan Gregg&rsquo;s blog</a> is a good
resource; there are some fantastic DTrace one liners.</p>

<h2>Debuggers</h2>

<h3>lldb</h3>

<p>lldb is analogous to gdb.  I can&rsquo;t say I have enough experience with LLDB and GDB to note the difference between the two, but LLDB did show the relative statements forward and back from the current statement by default.  I&rsquo;m informed by my friends/mortal enemies using emacs that this is less of an issue when using emacs/gdb in combination.</p>

<h2>Fuzzers</h2>

<h3>American Fuzzy Lop</h3>

<p><a href="http://lcamtuf.coredump.cx/afl/">American Fuzzy Lop</a> (AFL) is a neat program
that performs fuzzing on programs
that take inputs from files and repeatedly runs the program, modifies the
input trying to get full code coverage, and tries to find crashes.  It&rsquo;s been
getting lots of attention lately, and while I haven&rsquo;t used it myself yet, it
seems like a very powerful tool. Mozilla employs the use of fuzzers on their
JavaScript engine, for instance (not AFL, but
<a href="http://www.squarefree.com/2007/08/02/introducing-jsfunfuzz/">one developed in house</a>).</p>

<h2>Disassemblers</h2>

<h3>gobjdump</h3>

<p>If you really need to make sure the higher level code you&rsquo;re writing is getting
translated into the assembly your expecting, <code>gobjdump -S</code> will intermix the
emitted binary&rsquo;s disassembled assembly and the source code.  This was used
extensively while developing <a href="/blog/2015/05/25/interpreter-compiler-jit/">my Brainfuck JIT</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Hopefully you learned of some useful tools that you should know about when
working with C or C++.  What did I miss?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rust: Pattern Matching and the Option Type]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/05/07/rust-pattern-matching-and-the-option-type/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T18:41:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/05/07/rust-pattern-matching-and-the-option-type</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I was thinking about the function for performing dynamic memory
allocation in the C standard library, malloc. From the manual pages,
<code>If successful, the malloc() function returns a pointer to allocated memory.
If there is an error, it
returns a NULL pointer and sets errno to ENOMEM.</code> One of the most common errors
when using malloc is not checking for allocation failure.  The allocation is not
guaranteed to succeed and trying to use a NULL reference can lead to program
crashes.</p>

<p>So a common pattern we&rsquo;ll see is:</p>

<p><code>c C
int* nums = (int*) malloc(sizeof(int));
if (nums == NULL) {
  // handle error
} else {
  *nums = 7;
  // operate on nums
  free(nums);
  nums = NULL;
}
</code></p>

<p>Here we allocated space for an integer, cast the <code>void*</code> returned from malloc
to an <code>int*</code>, compared it against the <code>NULL</code> pointer, then freed the allocated
memory and removed the reference.</p>

<p>One of the big problems with the null pointer has to do with
safely dereferencing it.  In C, dereferencing the null pointer is undefined
and usually leads to a segfault and program crash.</p>

<p>It can be so unsafe to work with null pointers that
C. A. R. Hoare refers to them as his billion-dollar mistake:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I call it my billion-dollar mistake. It was the invention of the null reference in 1965. At that time, I was designing the first comprehensive type system for references in an object oriented language (ALGOL W). My goal was to ensure that all use of references should be absolutely safe, with checking performed automatically by the compiler. But I couldn&rsquo;t resist the temptation to put in a null reference, simply because it was so easy to implement. This has led to innumerable errors, vulnerabilities, and system crashes, which have probably caused a billion dollars of pain and damage in the last forty years.</p><footer><strong>C.A.R. Hoare</strong> <cite>InfoQ <a href="http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Null-References-The-Billion-Dollar-Mistake-Tony-Hoare">http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Null-References-The-Billion-Dollar-Mistake-Tony-Hoare</a> Null References: The Billion Dollar Mistake</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>So how do we represent the value of nothing?  With an integer, for example, your
first instinct might be to use 0 to refer to no value.  But 0 <em>is</em> a value, so
how do we represent the range of integer values but also whether there is a
value or not?</p>

<p>Rust, a systems programming language with a focus on safety and concurrency,
does not have the concept of a null pointer.  Instead, it has a different
construct to represent the absence of value, a whole other structure called an
<a href="http://static.rust-lang.org/doc/core/option.html">Option<T></a>.  It is an
<a href="http://static.rust-lang.org/doc/core/option.html#enum-option">enumerated type</a> that can
either be None (no value) or Some(T) (a specialization of type T).</p>

<p>So what the heck is an option type and how do we use it?  The option type is
a polymorphic type (generic type that can be specialized) that encapsulates
either an empty constructor or the constructor of the original data type.  Let&rsquo;s
take a trip down the rabbit hole to see how we use one.  First, let&rsquo;s look at
some C++ code, and then translate it to Rust.</p>

<p>```c++ option.cpp</p>

<h1>include <iostream> // cout, endl</h1>

<h1>include &lt;stdlib.h> // rand</h1>

<h1>include &lt;time.h> // time</h1>

<p>using namespace std;</p>

<p>// If there is a &lsquo;random error&rsquo; returns NULL
const int* const may_return_null () {
  srand(time(NULL));
  return rand() % 2 == 1 ? new int(666) : NULL;
}</p>

<p>int main () {
  // if else
  const int* const x = may_return_null();
  if (x) {</p>

<pre><code>// switch
switch (*x) {
  case 777: cout &lt;&lt; "Lucky Sevens"        &lt;&lt; endl; break;
  case 666: cout &lt;&lt; "Number of the Beast" &lt;&lt; endl; break;
  case 42: cout  &lt;&lt; "Meaning of Life"     &lt;&lt; endl; break;
  default: cout  &lt;&lt; "Nothing special"     &lt;&lt; endl; break;
}
</code></pre>

<p>  } else {</p>

<pre><code>cout &lt;&lt; "No value" &lt;&lt; endl;
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  // single if
  if (*x == 666) {</p>

<pre><code>cout &lt;&lt; "Did I mention that Iron Maiden is my favorite band?" &lt;&lt; endl;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s step through this program line by line, starting in main.</p>

<p><code>c++ Line 14
const int* const x = may_return_null();
</code></p>

<p>Here we&rsquo;re calling a function that may return null, just like malloc!</p>

<p><code>c++ Lines 8-9
srand(time(NULL));
return rand() % 2 == 1 ? new int(666) : NULL;
</code></p>

<p>In the body of <code>may_return_null</code> we seed the random number generator, generate a random number, mod it by 2
(so it can either be 0 or 1, 50-50 chance, hopefully), then either return a
pointer pointing to memory allocated on the heap or the null pointer.  We also use the succinct
ternary operator, which gives us the power of a conditional statement in the
form of a concise expression.</p>

<p><code>c++ Line 15
if (x) {
</code></p>

<p>We check if the pointer is valid, that is that it is safe to use, as <code>NULL</code> is
falsy in a C++ conditional.  If it is, then we can safely dereference it.  Let&rsquo;s
switch on the (dereferenced) value.  Notice how we need to break to explicitly
prevent fall through, though
<a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=4vm2xK3yn34C&amp;pg=PA37&amp;lpg=PA38&amp;dq=expert+c+fallthrough&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Ho98ZhXF9X&amp;sig=PebysT8-3zA_9B2aRkuvnz4mCmY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=j8CJUdeWMerJiwLQmICoDw&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=expert%20c%20fallthrough&amp;f=false">97% of the time that&rsquo;s what you intend</a>.</p>

<p><code>c++ Lines 17-22
switch (*x) {
  case 777: cout &lt;&lt; "Lucky Sevens"        &lt;&lt; endl; break;
  case 666: cout &lt;&lt; "Number of the Beast" &lt;&lt; endl; break;
  case 42: cout  &lt;&lt; "Meaning of Life"     &lt;&lt; endl; break;
  default: cout  &lt;&lt; "Nothing special"     &lt;&lt; endl; break;
}
</code></p>

<p>If the pointer was null, the else branch of the conditional would execute
printing a different result.</p>

<p><code>c++ Line 24
cout &lt;&lt; "No value" &lt;&lt; endl;
</code></p>

<p>Finally in we check the value pointed to.  Did I forget something here?  Save
that thought, we&rsquo;ll come back to it.</p>

<p><code>c++ Lines 28-30
if (*x == 666) {
  cout &lt;&lt; "Did I mention that Iron Maiden is my favorite band?" &lt;&lt; endl;
}
</code></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see my rough translation of this program into Rust.</p>

<p>```rust option.rs
use core::rand;</p>

<p>fn may_return_none () &ndash;> Option<int> {
  if rand::Rng().next() % 2 == 1 { Some(666) } else { None }
}</p>

<p>fn main () {
  let x: Option<int> = may_return_none();</p>

<p>  io::println(match x {</p>

<pre><code>Some(777) =&gt; "Lucky Sevens",
Some(666) =&gt; "Number of the Beast",
Some(422) =&gt; "Meaning of Life",
Some(_) =&gt; "Nothing special",
None =&gt; "No value"
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  match x {</p>

<pre><code>Some(666) =&gt; {
  io::println("Did I mention that Iron Maiden is my favorite Band?")
},
_ =&gt; {}
</code></pre>

<p>  };
}
```</p>

<p>Both programs, when compiled <em>should</em> randomly print either:</p>

<p><code>
No Value
// or
Number of the Beast
Did I mention that Iron Maiden is my favorite Band?
</code></p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s walk through the Rust code, starting at main and compare it to the
equivalent C++ code.</p>

<p><code>rust option.rs Line 8
let x: Option&lt;int&gt; = may_return_none();
</code>
<code>c++ option.cpp Line 14
const int* const x = may_return_null();
</code></p>

<p>I read this Rust code as &lsquo;let x be type Option,
specialized to type int initialized
to the return value of may_return_none.&rsquo;  I read the C++ as &lsquo;x is a const pointer
to a const integer initialized to the return value of may_return_none.&rsquo;  It&rsquo;s
important to note that values and pointers in Rust default to being immutable,
where as in c++ they default to being mutable, which is why we need to be
explicit about their const'ness.  In Rust, we could declare x as being explicitly
mutable: <code>let mut x: ... = ...;</code>.  In both, we can also leave the explicit types
to be inferred by the compiler.</p>

<p><code>rust option.rs Line 4
if rand::Rng().next() % 2 == 1 { Some(666) } else { None }
</code>
<code>c++ option.cpp Lines 8-9
srand(time(NULL));
return rand() % 2 == 1 ? new int(666) : NULL;
</code></p>

<p>Now for the body of <code>may_return_none</code>.  Rust does not have a ternary operator,
so a single line <code>if {} else {}</code> block will have to do.  We also don&rsquo;t need
parentheses around the predicate in the conditional statement.  If we add them,
no harm is done, as we&rsquo;d just be being redundant about order of operations.
There
are no semicolons in this expression, nor a return statement in this function.
Rust will return the last expression in a function or method if the semicolon is
left off.  Also there is no such thing as a conditional statement, only
conditional expressions; the if is itself something that can be evaluated and
assigned to a variable!  We see this later in the code where we pass the evaluation
of a match expression directly into a call of <code>io::println</code>.
Rust returns the evaluation of the if expression,
which is the evaluation of the branch&rsquo;s block specified by the predicate,
which will randomly be one of the two enumerated types of <code>Option&lt;int&gt;</code>, either
an encapsulation of a int whose literal value is <code>666</code>, <code>Some&lt;666&gt;</code>, or
the representation of no value, <code>None</code>.  I believe the RNG code has changed in 0.7,
this code was written in 0.6.</p>

<p>In Rust, to get the value out of an option type, we pattern match on it.  Pattern
matching is something I became familiar with through the
<a href="http://learnyouahaskell.com/syntax-in-functions#pattern-matching">Haskell</a> programming language.  Pattern
matching is a powerful language construct that can entirely replace conditionals.
In fact, the one line if expression could have been written using a match
expression:</p>

<p><code>rust
if rand::Rng().next() % 2 == 1 { Some(666) } else { None }
// or
match rand::Rng().next() % 2 { 1 =&gt; Some(666), _ =&gt; None }
</code></p>

<p>The basic design pattern
for accessing the value of an option type in Rust looks like:</p>

<p><code>rust
match x { // x: Option&lt;T&gt;
  Some(y) =&gt; { *y },
  None =&gt; {}
}
</code></p>

<p>The curly braces are optional for one liners (no block needed).
Pattern matches have to be exhaustive.  That means I have to exhaust all
possibilities for what the deconstructed value could be.  You can use a branch
that looks like:</p>

<p><code>rust
_ =&gt; 'everything else'
</code></p>

<p>to catch everything else.  The underscore here means &ldquo;every other possible case.&rdquo;
So by having to use a match expression (also not a
statement, as opposed to C++&rsquo;s switch statement), which itself must be exhaustive,
Rust forces us to handle the case where the optional type is None!  This will
help us again in the future.
We also don&rsquo;t need parentheses around the predicate for the match expression, which
in this case is just a single variable, <code>x</code>.</p>

<p>In the value
<code>Some(_)</code>, the underscore has an additional meaning here that we would not use a
variable in the corresponding arm&rsquo;s block.  If we declared it as <code>Some(y)</code> we would get the warning:</p>

<p><code>``
option.rs:14:9: 14:11 warning: unused variable:</code>y`
option.rs:14     Some(y) => &ldquo;Nothing special&rdquo;,</p>

<pre><code>                  ^~
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>I hope back in my C++ code you spotted the fatal flaw.  On line 28, I just
dereferenced a raw pointer without checking its validity.  This is a violation
of memory safety.</p>

<p><code>c++ option.cpp Line 28
if (*x == 666) {
</code></p>

<p>When running the C++ code, instead of seeing <code>No value</code> printed to stdout in the
case of no value, a segfault occurs.</p>

<p><code>
No value
[1]    80265 segmentation fault  ./option
</code></p>

<p>What I should have done is something more like:</p>

<p><code>c++ Line 28 corrected
if (x &amp;&amp; *x == 666) {
</code></p>

<p>But, the C++ compiler let me get away with not handling the case where the
pointer was invalid (even if doing nothing in the case of &ldquo;handling&rdquo; it).  By
leaving out the check for a valid pointer, I have instructed the machine to
behave the same or follow the same code path with and without a reference to a
valid memory location.  Let&rsquo;s see what happens when I don&rsquo;t handle the None case
by deleting line 15 or option.rs, <code>None =&gt; "No value"</code>:</p>

<p><code>
option.rs:10:14: 16:3 error: non-exhaustive patterns: None not covered
option.rs:10   io::println(match x {
option.rs:11     Some(777) =&gt; "Lucky Sevens",
option.rs:12     Some(666) =&gt; "Number of the Beast",
option.rs:13     Some(42) =&gt; "Meaning of Life",
option.rs:14     Some(_) =&gt; "Nothing special"
</code></p>

<p>Not only did the compiler prevent me from generating an executable, it told me
that a pattern was not exhaustive, explicitly which one, and what case that was
not covered.</p>

<p>Coming back to encoding a lack of value for an int, we had left off that 0 <em>is</em>
a valid value.  For instance, how should we represent any other integer divided
by 0, as an integer?
Signed integers use a single bit to store whether
their value is positive or negative, the tradeoff being the signed integers
represent up to one less power of two than unsigned integers.  Maybe we could use an
additional bit to represent valid or invalid, but this would again cost us in
terms of representable values.
The IEEE 754 floating point representation has encodings for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_floating_point#Formats">plus and minus
Infinity, plus and minus 0, and two kinds of NaN</a>.
To solve the validity problem, we can use enumerated types, which in Rust occur
as specializations of the Option type.  It&rsquo;s up to the compiler to implement
either additional information for the type, or use raw null pointers.  And to
get the value back out of the Option type, we <em>must</em> handle the case where there
is no valid value.</p>

<p>The key takeaways that I wish to convey are:</p>

<ol>
<li>In C and C++, I can use NULL to refer to a pointer that has no value.</li>
<li>A C/C++ compiler, such as clang, will allow me to compile code that violates
memory safety, such as dereferencing NULL pointers.</li>
<li>Rust instead uses Option types, an enumeration of a specialized type or None.</li>
<li>Rust forces me to use a match statement to access the possible value of an
Option type.</li>
<li>Pattern matching in Rust must be exhaustive.</li>
<li>The Rust compiler, rustc, forces me to handle the case where the pointer has
no value, whereas the C++ compiler, clang++, did not.</li>
<li>All conditional and switch statements can be replaced with pattern matching.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
