<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Internet | Nick Desaulniers]]></title>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/categories/internet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-01T18:58:13-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nick Desaulniers]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Commandments of a Mobile Web]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/02/28/commandments-of-a-mobile-web/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-28T22:43:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/02/28/commandments-of-a-mobile-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few years, there&rsquo;s been certain
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paradigm_shift">paradigm shifts</a>
in web development. When you think of milestones that really changed how
development on the web was done, the two biggest were
<a href="https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/mydeveloperworks/blogs/BobZurek/entry/the_ajax_paradigm_shift?lang=en">Ajax</a>
and <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/why">HTML5</a>.  Development was identifiably
different before and after such technological advancements.  There were
<a href="http://java.sys-con.com/node/315210">some</a> who initially
<a href="http://blog.tobie.me/post/31366970040/when-im-introspective-about-the-last-few-years-i">doubted</a>
the technologies, but I&rsquo;m sure such doubters eventually
<a href="http://www.sencha.com/blog/the-making-of-fastbook-an-html5-love-story/">saw the light</a>.
After spending time working on applications for Mozilla&rsquo;s upcoming mobile
operating system, Firefox OS, and talking with my fellow employees, I feel that
the mobile web is another one of those shifts in how we
approach web development that looking back will be an identifiable point in
time where we can say that we did things differently before and after.
So in that sense, I want to share some of the insights I&rsquo;ve found to
help other developers wrap their heads around how developing for the mobile web
isn&rsquo;t their traditional cup of tea.</p>

<h1>Internet connectivity is not guaranteed</h1>

<p>This is a fundamental divorce from the World Wide Web and the Internet. I feel
that a lot of people having trouble differentiating the Web from the Internet;
where you&rsquo;ve had one, you&rsquo;ve always had the other. Don&rsquo;t
assume your application will always have a valid connection.  When a user
is on a wifi connection, or hardwired, it&rsquo;s so obvious that if they&rsquo;re on your
website, then they must be connected to the Internet.  Right?  But what happens
now when one of your users loads up your site or app on a mobile device, then enters
a tunnel?  What does it do when offline?  Does it work?  Maybe it
doesn&rsquo;t make sense if you&rsquo;re offering a service that requires data from the
back end, but does that mean that the front end should totally look like crap
or break when the back end can&rsquo;t be reached?  Do your Ajax requests have error
callbacks?  Do you try and reconnect your WebSocket connections after they&rsquo;ve
failed?  Do you cache previous requests or use one of the many forms of offline
storage to show something to the user?  Developing on the loopback is literally
the best case for connectivity, but it gives the developer a false sense of
how latency and connectivity issues affect their application.  It&rsquo;s literally
shocking the first time you encounter your site/application offline if you
didn&rsquo;t think about the user experience up front.</p>

<h1>Bandwidth is not free</h1>

<p>The advent of broadband made it acceptable for sites to utilize massive amounts
of assets.  Seeing sites that load up so much stuff makes my heart sink when
I wonder about viewing such a site on my mobile device.  I only pay for so much
mobile data per month, then I&rsquo;m billed ridiculous amounts as a
<a href="http://forums.att.com/t5/Data-Messaging-Features-Internet/What-does-quot-Data-MB-Overage-quot-mean/td-p/2872883">&ldquo;Data Overage&rdquo;</a>.
Users in other countries frequently have a more pay as you go style plan, so
they&rsquo;re being billed for each bit across the wire.  In countries without the
infrastructure necessary to get broadband Internet to every household, mobile
is more prolific in getting users connected.</p>

<p>Things like minification and gzip certainly help, but deferred loading of
assets until they&rsquo;re necessary is frequently overlooked.
Massive libraries are nice for devs, but may end up giving mobile users more
problems than they are worth. There exist more advanced techniques such as
<a href="http://buildnewgames.com/optimizing-websockets-bandwidth/">WebSocket compression</a>.</p>

<p>How much does your site <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/minimizing-page-weight-matters/">weigh</a>?</p>

<h1>An expensive website does not make an awesome app</h1>

<p><blockquote><p>Why doesn&rsquo;t my million dollar website make a kick ass web app?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>This point is brought to you by <a href="http://www.mattbasta.com/">Matt Basta</a>.  The
point is that there is something fundamentally different between a web &ldquo;site&rdquo;
and a web &ldquo;app&rdquo;.  In a web site the usual flow involves loading up a page
and maybe navigating between pages.  An app more often than not will be a
single page that loads data asynchronously and dynamically modifies the content
displayed to the user.  Some web sites make great use of things like Ajax, and
are great example of single page sites.  But not all are.  Some still haven&rsquo;t
come around to loading all data asynchronously on request.  And it&rsquo;s not that
they necessarily even have to, they can be a website and never have to be
anything more.  But you&rsquo;ll find that some sites make better apps than others.</p>

<h2>No chrome</h2>

<p>Not the browser made by Google, Google Chrome; the actual
<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Chrome">controls</a> on the top
of your browser such as the back and reload buttons, and the url bar.  This
point comes from <a href="https://github.com/cvan">Chris Van Wiemeersch</a>.  One of
the things you&rsquo;ll find when evaluating whether a site makes a good app is
whether it relies on chrome to navigate.  If it does, then it&rsquo;s not really
going to cut it as an app.  If you&rsquo;re going to make a single page app, try
making it fullscreen in your browser and try navigating around. Are you
hindered without the chrome?  One thing I
found recently was an error condition where I notified the user that they had
to be online to check for an update.  But when I was developing, I would just
refresh the page to clear the error message and try again.  On a device, as an
app, where there was no chrome, this meant closing and restarting the app.
That sucked, so I made it so the user could click/touch, after figuring out
their connectivity issues, to retry the fetch.  Even better may have
been to listen for online events!</p>

<h2>Traditional forms of input are not fun</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s some tips from <a href="http://potch.me/">Matthew &ldquo;Potch&rdquo; Claypotch</a>.</p>

<h3>Fingers aren&rsquo;t as precise as cursors</h3>

<p>Having tiny click
targets is really frustrating.  How many times have you clicked the wrong
thing on a mobile device?  Tiny buttons are not the easiest thing for users
to specify, especially when groups of them are clustered nearby.  Custom
buttons enabled by <a href="http://www.cssbuttongenerator.com/">a little CSS</a> can go a
long way.</p>

<h3>Typing on little keyboards in tedious</h3>

<p>This is an effect of tiny buttons, but requiring the user to type in large
strings gets annoying fast.  Sometimes this can&rsquo;t be avoided, but it should be
when it can.  Just as typing in a long, complex url to a mobile browser is
not enjoyable, neither is doing so in an app.</p>

<h1>Detect features not browser engine (User agent sniffing is a sin)</h1>

<p>Print <a href="http://diveintohtml5.com/everything.html">this</a> and staple it to your
wall above your workspace.  This should be
<a href="http://www.nczonline.net/blog/2009/12/29/feature-detection-is-not-browser-detection/">old</a>
<a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/hh475813.aspx">news</a> at this point.</p>

<h2>Vendor prefixes are meant for browser vendors to test, not production code</h2>

<p>I place a majority of the blame for this on vendors; prefixes should never see
the light of day in release builds.  It&rsquo;s ridiculous to have to write four
copies of the same rule, when you&rsquo;re trying to express one thing.  I should
rewrite this sentence four different ways to prove a point.  -o-Do you understand
what I&rsquo;m getting at?  -ms-It&rsquo;s almost like rambling. -moz-Repetitive department
of repetition. -webkit-This is ridiculous.</p>

<p>But developers need to recognize the habit as an addiction, and not feed it.
If you have, I forgive you.  Now stop doing it.</p>

<p>These two particular articles are just so good, it wouldn&rsquo;t do them justice to
try and summarize them.  Please go read them, I&rsquo;ll wait.
<a href="http://hsivonen.iki.fi/vendor-prefixes/">this</a>
and
<a href="http://www.quirksmode.org/blog/archives/2010/03/css_vendor_pref.html">this</a></p>

<h2>Developing towards WebKit and not HTML5 is a sin</h2>

<p>I understand that Google Chrome is your favorite browser, and I am so happy for
you; but it is not mine.  I&rsquo;ll be the first to admit that Google
caught all of the other browser vendors with their pants down, but when I see
pages that look flawless in Chrome and
not so hot in others, it reminds me of days when sites only worked in IE6.
Surely you remember <em>those</em> days.  I hate when content publishers try and
dictate which browser I should use to view their content.  I understand WebKit
based browsers dominant in mobile, but so did IE6 in desktop share at one point.
It&rsquo;s not unreasonable to expect users to use the most updated version of their
browser, but empower your users to choose their browser.  Don&rsquo;t take that
choice away from them.</p>

<p>A neat <a href="http://robertnyman.com/2013/02/14/webkit-an-objective-view/">point</a> by
<a href="http://robertnyman.com/">Robert Nyman</a> is that WebKit itself already has forks.
Can you imagine if there were eventually vendor prefixes for forks of WebKit?
Continuing with vendor prefixes means that we&rsquo;ll now have seven vendor prefixes:
unprefixed, -moz-, -o-, -ms-, -webkit-o-, -webkit-chrome-, -webkit-safari-.
Awesome!  Maybe I should rewrite this sentence seven different ways to make a
point!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also curious if Google, Apple, and the WebKit maintainers are turning a
blind eye to this, or what their opinions are? Being a vendor and wanting an
open web are almost conflicts of interest; you want your browser to &ldquo;win&rdquo; or
dominate in marketshare, but at the same time you don&rsquo;t want any one browser
having too much marketshare.</p>

<h1>Design Responsively</h1>

<p>What is
<a href="http://mashable.com/2012/12/11/responsive-web-design/">responsive design</a>?
<a href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/responsive-web-design-guidelines-tutorials/">Responsive design</a>
is making a site look great on
any size screen, without duplicating assets or sniffing a user agent string.
Firefox has a neat web dev tool called
<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Tools/Responsive_Design_View">&ldquo;Responsive Design View&rdquo;</a>.
It&rsquo;s great for testing out your site on various screen sizes.
<a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/index.html">Twitter Bootstrap</a> is an
excellent example of a framework for developing a single app that looks great
on any screen size.  Even if you don&rsquo;t want to use a whole big framework,
simple things like using CSS rules in terms of percentages instead of hard
coded pixels can go a long way.</p>

<p>Sites that are trying to become more app like have trouble with conforming to
responsive design.  Instead of starting with a site and trying to figure out
how to hide
or not display information as the screen gets smaller, you&rsquo;ll find it much
<a href="http://johnpolacek.github.com/scrolldeck.js/decks/responsive/">easier</a> to
start small, and dynamically add content as the screen gets bigger.</p>

<h1>High performance code respects battery life</h1>

<p>In the end of the day, all of the code you write that runs in the browser is
a set of instructions the processor can decode, not necessarily the high level
JavaScript you wrote.  While it&rsquo;s important to avoid premature optimizations,
having a few
<a href="http://christianheilmann.com/2013/01/25/five-things-you-can-do-to-make-html5-perform-better/">rules of thumb</a>
up front will help you write better, faster code.
If the same overall action can be expressed in one instruction or one hundred,
which do you think will use
<a href="http://coding.smashingmagazine.com/2012/11/05/writing-fast-memory-efficient-javascript/">less power</a>?
Keep in mind that transistors leak current while switching.</p>

<h2>Native methods over library methods, CSS over JS</h2>

<p>What do I mean by &ldquo;native methods?&rdquo; Like C++?  Well, yes.  You see under the
hood the DOM bindings that you&rsquo;re calling are probably written in C++.  Call
<code>toSource()</code> on <code>document.getElementById()</code>.  The <code>[native code]</code> statement
in the returned string refers to the implementation.  While type specialized
code emitted by the JIT can match or even beat native code, you can only count
on that for hot loops.  In the same vein, library code is going to be
<a href="http://jsperf.com/getelementbyid-vs-jquery-id/25">slower</a> than any code
written natively.  I&rsquo;m not saying that you shouldn&rsquo;t use libraries, just know
that the use of libraries can incur some overhead.  Things like animations will
also be faster
when handled by natively implemented CSS over JS.  You can use JS to
dynamically add classes to elements to get finer resolution over events, but
then get the performance of CSS.</p>

<h2>Avoid JIT bailout</h2>

<p>The Just In Time (JIT) interpreter is a
<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/amdgigabyte/know-your-javascript-engine">new breed</a>
of VM that most browser
vendors are now using.  The JIT can
<a href="http://s3.mrale.ph/nodecamp.eu/#1">analyze</a> running code, and
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_generation_%28compiler%29#Runtime_code_generation">emit</a>
native code
that is faster than reinterpreting code again, and even higher-optimized code
for type stable JavaScript, as long as certain &ldquo;guard&rdquo; conditions are met.
When a guard fails, the JIT has to
<a href="http://mxr.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/source/js/src/ion/Bailouts.h#19">bailout</a>
the emitted native code and start reinterpreting code again.</p>

<h2>Keep up to date on new APIs</h2>

<p>HTML5 is a big
<a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/single-page.html">spec</a>, and is
getting bigger.  So big that some recommendations are
being <a href="http://www.websocket.org/aboutwebsocket.html">spun off</a> from the
original HTML5 spec.  As an engineer, I&rsquo;m painfully aware that you need to
<a href="http://bonsaiden.github.com/JavaScript-Garden/">keep up</a>
in whatever industry you work in in order to stay relevant.
The complacent are the most vulnerable.  There&rsquo;s
<a href="http://caniuse.com/">a lot to keep track of</a> with
HTML5 and CSS3, but many new features offer higher performance methods of
skinning the cat.</p>

<h3>requestAnimationFrame</h3>

<p>window.requestAnimation frame is a godsend for animation.  Not too long ago, I
wrote up a quick
<a href="https://github.com/nickdesaulniers/canvas2dcontext/blob/master/examples/sprite.html#L6">example</a>
of various ways of implementing animation loops and their issues; you should
check it out.</p>

<h3>indexedDB over localstorage</h3>

<p>The indexedDB api might not be as simple as localstorage&rsquo;s is, but localstorage
is synchronous and is noticeably slow on mobile.  If you can bite the bullet
and use indexedDB, you&rsquo;ll find you&rsquo;re JS isn&rsquo;t blocking on
serializing/deserializing objects for storage.
<a href="https://twitter.com/fabricedesre">Fabrice Desré</a> shared this with me.</p>

<h3>WebWorkers</h3>

<p>Webworkers can&rsquo;t modify the DOM, but they can do heavy lifting without blocking
the main thread.</p>

<h3>CSS translate over absolute top and left rules</h3>

<p><a href="http://digitarald.de/">Harald Kirschner</a> recommends CSS translates over top
and left rules for absolutely positioning some elements.</p>

<h3>Gradients are expensive</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.backalleycoder.com/">Dan Buchner</a> notes that without beefy graphics
processing units of their desktop counterparts to enable hardware acceleration,
things like gradients will give you noticeable performance hits.</p>

<h3>createDocumentFragment</h3>

<p>Dan also suggests queuing up DOM changes.
Whenever you manipulate items in the DOM, you&rsquo;re going to trigger a reflow,
which may consist of an update to the layout and/or a repaint.  Minimizing these
makes for a faster update to the DOM.  For example, it can be faster to use
document.createDocumentFragment and append child nodes to it, and then append
that to the DOM, instead of appending lots of child nodes in between timer calls.
Surprise, this isn&rsquo;t actually a
<a href="http://ejohn.org/blog/dom-documentfragments/">new</a> DOM binding from HTML5.</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>These are just some tips I have for application developers.  I am by no means
an expert; I&rsquo;m sure if you dig deep enough, you can find plenty of examples of
my past work that contradicts some of my recommendations from this article.  But
I&rsquo;m a little smarter today than I was yesterday, and now so are you!  What are some
tips that you have to share that you&rsquo;ve found helpful developing for the
mobile web?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Internet] Freedom is Not Free]]></title>
    <link href="http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/01/19/internet-freedom-is-not-free/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-19T20:12:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2013/01/19/internet-freedom-is-not-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, the Internet community
<a href="http://tech.mit.edu/V132/N61/swartz.html">lost</a> a member in the on going war
against the copyright industry.  While I&rsquo;ve never met the deceased, or
even heard of the deceased before his suicide, I&rsquo;m horrified.  I&rsquo;m
horrified that the government we are asked to put so much faith in,
would give someone, not that different from myself, such a <a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20120917/17393320412/us-government-ups-felony-count-jstoraaron-swartz-case-four-to-thirteen.shtml">ridiculous sentence</a>.
That I could be thrown away, locked away from the things that
I love for 35 years, for freeing information that
<a href="http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2013/01/aaron-swartz-memorial-jstor-liberator-sets-public-domain-academic-articles-free/">should</a>
have been free, and was later
<a href="http://www.3news.co.nz/Reddit-co-founder-dies-weeks-before-trial/tabid/412/articleID/282905/Default.aspx">made</a> free.</p>

<p>That my government would strike such fear into someone&rsquo;s life that they
would prefer death by their own hands to punishment.  Why do we put up
with this?</p>

<p>The Internet, and the technology sector evolves so quickly.  It&rsquo;s
amazing that the law the deceased was being prosecuted under, pertaining
to computers, is from
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Fraud_and_Abuse_Act">1986</a>.  Can
you even remember what computers were like in 1986?  I didn&rsquo;t even
exist!  My first family computer ran Windows 95.  I can only imagine how
archaic laws would be that were based on such rapidly evolving tech.</p>

<p>The limiting of information is problematic to me.  How do the people of
China, Iran, and others feel about their government?  I assume they are
aware that the government is limiting their body of knowledge.  Even the
US television news agencies can&rsquo;t get the story straight.  It
reminds me of George Orwell&rsquo;s <em>1984</em>, where the language is limited to
curtail expression.  If the free world uses the Internet as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transactive_memory">Transactive Memory</a>, does the
oppressed world know what they&rsquo;re missing?  Can you know what you&rsquo;re
missing, before you&rsquo;ve lost it?</p>

<p>The media and copyright lobby disgust me.  I&rsquo;m disgusted that <a href="http://www.mpaa.org/about/ceo">my former state senator</a>
is now the Chairman and
CEO of the MPAA.  Remember learning in high school civics the term
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revolving_door_%28politics%29">&ldquo;Revolving Door&rdquo;</a>? Case
in point.</p>

<p>America was constitutionalized as a republic, but through
amendment has <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic_republic">evolved</a>
into a democratic republic.  The idea of a republic was important to an
<a href="http://seattletimes.com/html/nationworld/2003332210_tuesday31.html">agrarian society</a>,
and we still feel the effects every first Tuesday in
November; the least convenient day of the week.  Voting for someone
just to represent you was convenient when your form of long-range
communication was a man on a pony.  With the rise of the Internet, and
representatives who work for their lobbies and not the people,
why do we still elect officials?  Why are we a republic?  Why not just a
democracy?  Allow voters to authenticate and cast their vote online.
Everyone.  No computer or internet?  I&rsquo;m sure your local library offers
both free for public use.  &ldquo;But people don&rsquo;t always know what&rsquo;s right.&rdquo;
Sure, I think some people aren&rsquo;t too bright.  But then I see the
deadlock in congress, fiscal cliff after fiscal cliff, and I can&rsquo;t help
but think we could do better if we just fired all of these assholes.</p>

<p>Why can&rsquo;t the difference in viewpoints be celebrated?  A good leader
recognizes both sides of the coin.  I love having a diverse team of
people with varying backgrounds, because they come up with solutions I
never could have.  And if you want to beat your enemy, you have to know
your enemy.  That means empathizing, understanding where they come from.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>If you give orders and explain nothing, you might get obedience, but<br/>you&rsquo;ll get no creativity. If you tell them your purpose, then when your<br/>original plan is shown to be faulty, they&rsquo;ll find another way to achieve<br/>your goal. Explaining to your men doesn&rsquo;t weaken their respect for you,<br/>it proves your respect for them.</p><footer><strong>Han Tzu</strong> <cite>Shadow of the Giant Pg. 303 by Orson Scott Card</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t hate anyone for what they believe, nor do I
try to persuade them otherwise.  I just feel like the technologically
minded are under represented in Washington.  I wish we had a
technological party.  We need a
party that strives to protect the internet, the ideals behind
the freedom and preservation of information, the technical investment in
sovereign energy and our failing infrastructure, and internet access
speeds that are unrivaled in the world, not stagnated by corporations
who are relatively regional monopolies.  One where social
issues are open to debate, but also where protecting our greatest asset and
achievement is top priority.  One where the media industry is invited to
the table, unlike the back door <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Online_Piracy_Act">policies</a>
they would try to slip in under our noses.  My dad advocated a turn the
other cheek policy.  That&rsquo;s called acting like an adult.</p>

<p>My belief of good vs. evil is that there is no good or evil, but that people
are inherently selfish.  They
do things that are perceived by others as evil.  But they don&rsquo;t do
things because those actions are evil, they do them because they gain
some form of personal utility from the action; they perceive the action
as good.  And it is good&hellip;to them.  It&rsquo;s easy to be evil.  It&rsquo;s the easy
way out.  It&rsquo;s harder to think about other people.  It&rsquo;s tougher to do
the right thing.  Being good is so recognizably hard; it&rsquo;s impressive.</p>

<p>The president of MIT, L. Rafael Reif, had this to say regarding the
deceased: <a href="http://touch.latimes.com/#section/-1/article/p2p-74009443/">&ldquo;It pains me to think that MIT played any role in a series of events that have ended in tragedy&hellip;&rdquo;</a>
Fuck you. Maybe if MIT&rsquo;s bottom line wasn&rsquo;t their acceptance rate, they
might be able to look out for more than just their own.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>All that is necessary for the triumph of evil is that good men do<br/>nothing.</p><footer><strong>Edmund Burke</strong> <cite>Thoughts on the Cause of Present Discontents</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Suicide is never the answer.  No matter how shitty your current
situation is, no matter if things will never go back to the way they
were, you will always be able to change your situation.  Maybe not
immediately, but that&rsquo;s what goals are for.  Anyone who ever committed
suicide to prove a point could have done more for their cause dedicating
the rest of their life to it.  If you&rsquo;re feeling depressed, talk to
someone.  It will make you feel so much better to talk to someone about
what&rsquo;s upsetting you.  As much as people like to shit on the Catholic
Church, I feel like the Catholic practice of penance (confession),
provides a cathartic placebo effect.  If you are depressed or hurting, and
you need someone to talk to, even a complete stranger, feel free to
contact me.  I will always provide an ear and a shoulder.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It seems strange that my life should end in such a terrible place, but<br/>for three years I had roses and apologized to no one. I shall die here.<br/>Every inch of me shall perish. Every inch, but one. An inch. It is small<br/>and it is fragile and it is the only thing in the world worth having. We<br/>must never lose it or give it away. We must NEVER let them take it from<br/>us. I hope that whoever you are, you escape this place. I hope that the<br/>world turns, and that things get better. But what I hope most of all is<br/>that you understand what I mean when I tell you that, even though I do<br/>not know you, and even though I may never meet you, laugh with you, cry<br/>with you, or kiss you, I love you. With all my heart, I love you.</p><footer><strong>Valerie</strong> <cite>V for Vendetta</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The next time the media industry tries to limit what you have access to
on the Internet, make a big ruckus.  Inform everyone you know about the
facts.  Pushing for an increase in media piracy activities is not the
right answer.  Instead we should push to boycott working for
organizations like the RIAA and MPAA and their ilk.  Think about how
much better off we would be in the United States if teachers were paid
like rock stars and rock stars were paid like teachers?  Instead, everyone
in the media industry needs a fat paycheck.  Celebrity is the case in
point of the blind leading the blind.  Did you know that EMI
<a href="https://mashable.com/2013/01/18/i-have-a-dream-internet-freedom/">owns</a>
the copyright to the footage of Martin Luther King&rsquo;s &ldquo;I have a
dream&rdquo; speech?  If you can find it, I bet it wont be up long.  Frankly,
I&rsquo;m surprised EMI doesn&rsquo;t also own the Declaration of Independence and
Constitution, charging admission.</p>

<p>Revolutions are a continuation of the battle between sword and shield.
Something new is created and shows potential, then doubters pop up
seeking to curtail that which upsets their competitive edge.  In the
case of information, many make money and become powerful off
limiting the access to knowledge.  I think all knowledge that is
beneficial to mankind should be open, and that the Internet is the ultimate
utility for the sharing of our collective knowledge.  Where do you draw
the line, you might ask?  I think the knowledge required to make atomic
weapons and 3D-print receivers is decidedly unbefitting of society,
for instance.
And in the end, you can&rsquo;t take any of the knowledge you protect with
you.  If everyone shared what they knew, then you&rsquo;d have a more
improved life, since then the right people would be
in the know to advance our being.  Technology would advance even faster
than it does currently if we weren&rsquo;t limited to
<a href="http://www.techradar.com/us/news/computing-components/processors/why-intels-new-cpus-disappoint-1077260">tick-tock</a> product
cycles and business secrets.</p>

<p>So what does a rant about government, antiquated laws, corrupt
representatives, celebrating diversity, hypothetical political parties,
inaction, and established industries have to do with anything?
They&rsquo;re all anchored to a suicide.  They&rsquo;re all that&rsquo;s been running
through my mind lately.  What I see in the deceased, I see in myself.
Standing amongst my peers, celebrating <a href="http://www.internetfreedomday.net/">Internet Freedom Day</a>
, listening to <a href="https://www.eff.org/about/staff/peter-eckersley">Peter Eckersley</a> of the
<a href="https://www.eff.org/">EFF</a> talk, I realized <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vo0D6bzxLLw">&lsquo;The power is
yours!&rsquo;</a>.
So now I add my voice to the or so 20 Internet activists that will continue to
spring up as one falls.</p>

<p>What will you do to shape the world you live in?  What are you going to do to
fix it?  If you don&rsquo;t, I will.  Because if you want something done
right, you have to do it yourself.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It has to start somewhere It has to start sometime<br/>What better place than here, what better time than now?</p><footer><strong>Rage Against the Machine</strong> <cite>Guerrilla Radio</cite></footer></blockquote></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
