<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>clang on Nick Desaulniers</title>
    <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/categories/clang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in clang on Nick Desaulniers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/categories/clang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Off by Two</title>
      <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2020/04/06/off-by-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2020/04/06/off-by-two/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;War stories&amp;rdquo; in programming are entertaining tales of truly evil bugs that kept you up at night. Inspired by posts like My Hardest Bug Ever, Debugging an evil Go runtime bug, and others from /r/TalesFromDebugging, I wanted to share with you one of my favorites from recent memory. Recent work has given me much fulfilment and a long list of truly awful bugs to recount. My blog has been quieter than I would have liked; hopefully I can find more time to document some of these, maybe in series form.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GCC vs LLVM Q3 2017 Commit Rates and Active Developer Counts</title>
      <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2017/09/05/gcc-vs-llvm-q3-2017-commit-rates-and-active-developer-counts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2017/09/05/gcc-vs-llvm-q3-2017-commit-rates-and-active-developer-counts/</guid>
      <description>A blog post from a few years ago that really stuck with me was Martin Olsson’s Browser Engines 2015: Commit Rates and Active Developer Counts, where he shows information about the number of authors and commits to popular web browsers. The graphs and analysis had interesting takeaways like showing the obvious split in blink and webkit, and relative number of contributors of the projects. Martin had data comparing gcc to llvm from Q4 2015, but I wanted to see what the data looked like now in Q3 2017 and wanted to share my findings; simply rerunning the numbers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Additional C/C&#43;&#43; Tooling</title>
      <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2015/07/23/additional-c-slash-c-plus-plus-tooling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2015/07/23/additional-c-slash-c-plus-plus-tooling/</guid>
      <description>21st Century C by Ben Klemens was a great read. It had a section with an intro to autotools, git, and gdb. There are a few other useful tools that came to mind that I&amp;rsquo;ve used when working with C and C++ codebases. These tools are a great way to start contributing to Open Source C &amp;amp; C++ codebases; running these tools on the code or adding them to the codebases.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
