<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>x86 on Nick Desaulniers</title>
    <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/categories/x86/</link>
    <description>Recent content in x86 on Nick Desaulniers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/categories/x86/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s in a Word?</title>
      <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/whats-in-a-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/05/15/whats-in-a-word/</guid>
      <description>Recently, there some was some confusion between myself and a coworker over the definition of a &amp;ldquo;word.&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on a blog post about data alignment and figured it would be good to clarify some things now, that we can refer to later.
Having studied computer engineering and being quite fond of processor design, when I think of a &amp;ldquo;word,&amp;rdquo; I think of the number of bits wide a processor&amp;rsquo;s general purpose registers are (aka word size).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Debugging X86-64 Assembly</title>
      <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/01/20/debugging-x86-64-assembly-with-lldb-and-dtrace/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2016/01/20/debugging-x86-64-assembly-with-lldb-and-dtrace/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m hacking on an assembly project, and wanted to document some of the tricks I was using for figuring out what was going on. This post might seem a little basic for folks who spend all day heads down in gdb or who do this stuff professionally, but I just wanted to share a quick intro to some tools that others may find useful. ( oh god, I&amp;rsquo;m doing it)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s Write Some X86-64</title>
      <link>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2014/04/18/lets-write-some-x86-64/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickdesaulniers.github.io/blog/2014/04/18/lets-write-some-x86-64/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;&amp;lsquo;Our speech interposes itself between apprehension and truth like a dusty pane or warped mirror. The tongue of Eden was like a flawless glass; a light of total understanding streamed through it. Thus Babel was a second Fall.&amp;rsquo; And Isaac the Blind, an early Kabbalist, said that, to quote Gershom Scholem&amp;rsquo;s translation, &amp;lsquo;The speech of men is connected with divine speech and all language whether heavenly or human derives from one source: the Divine Name.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
